Greetings everyone. In this video I will show
you the newest update of DreamBooth extension
of Automatic1111 web UI. The new update brought
huge improvement to teach our subjects into
Stable Diffusion models. It is like 10x better
than before. This will be a short video of
best settings. Therefore, if you are interested
in a detailed tutorial, please first watch
my very thorough DreamBooth tutorial.
Let me show you it.
This is the video that you need to watch. So
let me show you which commit, which version
of DreamBooth and SD web UI I am using. This
is the DreamBooth revision and this is the
SD web UI revision. To use these specific versions,
just open the Git Bash. You need
to install it from Google and then move to
your folder installation folder, like this
CD and drag and drop. Then use git checkout
command like this and paste the commit ID.
And now it will checkout to that version. With
the newest update, you are able to obtain
very highly stylized and very good results
with a very simple command like this. You
see, I just added Tomer Hanuka to my token, ohwx
and, as usually, I am using the negative
prompt and it is able to stylize it very well.
This is the data set I have used. It is not
great, but it is not also very bad. All of the
backgrounds and the clothes are different,
different angles. Okay, now let me show you the
best settings. This is not necessary, but
make sure that you have selected the version 1.5,
pruned ckpt here, or whatever the model
that you want to train on. Go to the DreamBooth tab
in the create menu. Give a name like tutorial.
Now we are checking whether that 512 pixel model
or not. Source checkpoint this is the
important one: version 1.5 pruned and create
model. You should get a message like this:
checkpoint successfully extracted to our working
folders. Go to the settings tab and in here
click performance wizard first. There is also
new LoRA version. However, I couldn't get
good results with LoRA yet. Hopefully I will
make another new video for LoRA, so I am not
picking it. Do not check this checkbox. It is
usually not working. By the way, with the
new model, with the new update, it is working
much faster than before. In terms of number
of epochs required to train your subject. For
example, I was able to teach my face with
just 30 epochs, unlike previously I was using
like 150 epochs. So still, you can set this
as 200, set this as 0, set this as 5 because
it is getting overtrained very quickly. With
the newest update I think they have fixed a lot
of things and now this is not automatically
checking. Checked for me. I have RTX 3060.
When you check this it will actually reduce
the memory usage, but it will slow down your
process and this is also for saving VRAM.
So this is constant with warmup. It is fine.
I didn't change the learning rate. It works
fine. Do not check this box and do not check
this checkbox as well. Here, this is very
important to understand whether you started overtraining
or not. So photo of ohwx man
by Tomer Hanuka. The ohwx is our token. It
is a very rare token and man is class token.
Then in the advanced tab, if you have more than
12GB VRAM, you can check this "use EMA".
It will improve your success. Use 8bit Adam.
We have 16bf and xformers. By the way, let me also
show you the command line arguments I used. The
only command line argument I used is
--xformers, and I am also using disable
safe unpicked. But this is not necessary.
I didn't add --no-half, because this
is necessary for SD version 2.1. This will
slow down your image generation and also training,
but this is all only necessary for SD 2.1.
So if you are not working with SD 2.1 version, do
not add this. It will slow down your process.
I am checking cache latents. This will speed
up the training but it will increase the
VRAM usage. Since I have 12GB, it works fine.
I am also training UNET. If you don't have
enough VRAM then you should uncheck this. Okay,
It gave an error when I unchecked it.
I think they will fix it. So I am leaving these
default. There is a new settings, as
you can see, the Weight Decay AdamW optimizer.
It says that this will more generalize your
images as you make this number bigger. If you
want your subject to be as close much
as to you. By default it is 0.01. I did left
it default and it worked very well. And the
pad tokens: these are for when you are using the
[filewords] and shuffle tags, image captions
related. There's also one new, another option:
prior loss. I asked this to the developer
of the extension developer. The answer of the developer
is this: As you can see, Scale prior loss
loss, decrease the prior loss weight as
training progress. When you enable it, you
get a "minimum prior loss" setting and
"prior loss target". The target is: at what epoch
should the prior loss weight reach the minimum.
He also commented as not sure if it matters
or helps, but it will stand to the reason that
as we train our model, we want the weight
of the class images to be lower than that the
instance images, as the model should already
better know the subject. I made test with enabling
this and disabling it. I think when this is
not enabled, it worked better for me, but
it is up to you to test it. Then we go to
the concept. Okay, In the directories, as usual,
we are setting our first training set
directory. This is my training set directory.
So I copied it, I pasted it, then set it
set a new. If you have prior classification images,
like I have, you can give it its directory
or you can give a new directory like this.
Okay, Now [filewords]. People are getting very
confused with this. Let I will explain to you
what is this actually in this video. Let's
say you have typed as ohwx here and you
have type of [filewords] here. So this will
become like this when it is processing. For example,
let's say I am using image captions,
like in this example, and the caption of the
image is like this. Okay, Let me show you.
So when I use the configuration like this,
it will append the instance token I
have written in the [filewords] to the beginning.
Then it will read the captions here.
So the final prompt will be like this. If
I also add a word here, let's say example
word, then this example word will be appended
here. So this is also equal to using like
this. When you use it like this, it will become
actually exact exactly like this. So this
is how [filewords] and instance token works.
I am not using any [filewords]
and image caption. So I am setting as
the instance token as ohwx man. So
the ohwx is our token and the man is our
class. In this video I have very clearly
and very detailedly and very technically explained
how the Stable Diffusion works, how
it is composed by vectors and different tokens.
For class prompt, we are using photo
of man and for sample image prompt: we
are using photo of ohwx man as you can
see, then, class images per instance,
I have used 48 images and in
the saving tab, make sure that you are generating
a ckpt file and saving during training
because, when you see it is over training,
you will see use the certain checkpoints
and then click save settings. Okay, I think
everything is pretty much ready and. Just
hit train tab and it will start generating
the classification images and after that
it will start training the model. You see,
the classification images are very weird
and. If you handpick the good classification
images then it may improve your success.
It is up to you to test. But I didn't touch
the classification images actually. I just
used whatever it generated. Okay, here
the training samples generated during
my training. So, as you can see, even in the
10th epoch this is the I have saved preview
images and checkpoints every 10 epoch. It is
already learned a very good my subject,
my face. And after 30 epochs we are losing
the styling with by using the sanity.
As you can see, in the sanity we used by Tomer
Hanuka style. So I decided to do my
tests on the just the 30 epochs and it worked
very well, as I have shown you. Also,
when we analyze that you see, now we don't
even need to increase the prompt emphasis
of our token, just using, like this, 1.1 emphasis,
and it is working, working very well.
And with 30 step and with 720 steps training,
it is able to fully stylize my face and able
to generate very beautiful images. This is different
than the previous trainings of the
DreamBooth extension of Automatic1111. So
therefore, now, the things are really
different, really improved I think what they
did is now they are properly able to keep
up the prior loss and previously they were
not able to keep that. So now, with a very
few number of epochs, the model is able to
learn our subject very well. You still
can do a test of different epochs, so to
do that, you just need to use the X/Y
plot and in here you can give the checkpoint
names. You see it's showing all of the names
like this and just delete the ones that you don't
want to test. And, the Y plot. I suggest
you to test CFG value. You can test 8, 7
9, 10, 11, 12 and whatever
you want. And when you do test you can see
which epoch is working best for you. And I
am really happy with the newest update because
it's certainly improved the training
quality. So check out the newest DreamBooth
extension. Thank you very much for watching.
Please like, subscribe and leave a comment.
You can join our discord channel and discuss
everything and ask any questions. Go to the
about tab of our YouTube channel and in the
bottom you will see official discord channel link.
And if you support us on Patreon, I would
appreciate very much. This is keeping me to
do more research and produce better quality
videos. Hopefully see you
later in another video.