Greetings everyone.
In this video I am going to show you how you can inject your subject, in this case my face,
into any custom model by using Automatic1111 Web UI.
So you see, the center image is my original
image and the other images are generated by
using this injected model, which is Protegen x3.4.
It's an awesome model to generate hyperrealistic pictures.
This is the official site.
So if you don't know how to use Automatic1111, I have great tutorials.
First of all, I have shown how to install Automatic 1111 and run it in this video.
And I have shown how to use different models
with Automatic1111 in this video.
And recently my published video shows how
you can train your subject, e.g. your face
or anything, by using Automatic 1111 and DreamBooth extension.
And if your graphic card is not very good but can support LoRA training, then I have
shown how to do LoRA training in this video.
Even though if you are still not able to train
your subject by using LoRA, if you still don't
have a decent graphic card, then don't worry.
I have shown how to use Google Colab to teach
your subject and then you can generate ckpt
file on Google Colab, download it and can
use it on Automatic1111 web UI.
And in this video I have shown how to use
custom models on Google Colab for training.
Now we can start.
By the way, I will put all of these videos
links into the description and they are all
available in our channel.
Go to our channel main page and in here you
will see Stable Diffusion DreamBooth playlist
and everything is available here.
I will also put the link of this to the description.
OK, now we can start.
So currently the selected model is my trained
model in the my last video.
I have trained my face by using 12 images.
So this is the training data set.
If you wonder what kind of data set was was
used, it's a pretty simple and small data
set: only 12 images.
OK, this is the image that the training model
can generate.
By the way, the training model is based on
SD 1.5 official version.
You see, it is a pretty bad quality actually.
So to get very good, very high quality images
on the default SD 1.5 version data set, you
have to generate insane amount of images and
you have to do a lot of prompt trying.
So you see, this is a pretty simple prompt
actually, and this is also a pretty simple
negative prompt.
So how are we going to inject our trained
model into a custom model.
First of all, as a primary model, we are going
to select the target model, which is Protegen
x3.4 in this case.
A photo realism model, a very high quality
model.
I have selected it from this drop down box:
Protegen x3.4, official.
Then the secondary model will be the model
that we will extract our trained subject,
which is web ui ohwx, my face trained model.
OK, let me select it.
And the tertiary model.
So what is tertiary model?
The strategy we are going to use is like this:
So the base model, which is the tertiary model,
C model.
In the base model, we are going to select
the base model that we used to train our subject,
which is version 1.5 Pruned ckpt.
And the trained model is model B, which is
Web UI owhx, and the target model is model
A. So what we are going to do is we are going
to subtract model C from model B. And what
will be left?
Only our trained subject will be left.
OK, because we have trained our subject, in
my case my face, and we have now the trained
model have my face and the rest is supposed
to be same with the base model.
And then we are going to inject our face into
our target model, which is Protegen.
So how are we going to do that?
First of all, we need to define a custom name.
I will say my face, Protegen, like this: So
multiplier.
What kind of model we want to get?
This is defining the strength of our injection.
For faces the community suggests 75 percent,
which is equal to zero point seventy five.
I have, I have made a lot of tests and I seen
that for my particular trained model, 95 percent
is working better.
Then you are selecting add difference here,
not the weighted sum.
We are going to use add selected add difference,
because this is the strategy that we are going
to use and generate ckpt.
You don't need to save as float16 Just click
run.
OK.
In the CMD window you will see that it is
loading the models then generating the target
model, like this: My face protogen ckpt and
the checkpoint saved.
Now let's go back to text image tab and click
refresh.
And now we can see my face protogen ckpt.
OK.
Now let's generate an image to see what kind
of quality we are going to get.
OK, this is the quality we got.
With just a try you can generate hundreds
of images and generate much higher quality
images.
The eye color is not matching, therefore I
should add also brown eyes here.
But there are several key issues.
The first key issue is that how did I come
up with this prompt strength 1.4 and how did
I picked The CFG value?
To do that.
It is very easy.
First of all, let's define a weight here,
weight_val, like this as you can see: OK,
this will be keyword that we are going to
use and for CFG value, we will set it here.
So I am going to X/Y plot.
So in the first value I am going to select
CFG.
To find the optimal CFG and weight values
for your newly generated compound or injected
model.
You should make a X/Y plot and see the which
one is producing the best outcome for you.
And for the Y values we are going to use prompt
SR, like this.
And in here we are going to put this as a
keyword.
And then we are going to set the prompt strength,
like 1.0, 1.1, 1.2, like this, and then 1.3.
Okay, 1.4.
All right, then do not check this box, because
we are going to compare the effect of prompt
strength and CFG values.
Therefore, do not check keep -1 for seeds.
For example, let's pick the batch size as
4 it will speed up if your graphic card VRAM
is sufficient.
I think this should be sufficient enough to
see the compare results and see which one
of the weight and the CFG value performs best
on our newly generated model.
After the results generated, just compare
them and see which one of the CFG value and
the weight produced the best outcome And then
you can use that weight value in your prompts
and the CFG value in your prompts.
So this methodology would work on any custom
model that is using the same base model version
as you are using.
So the if the models are trained on version
1.5, and if your custom model the subject
having model trained on version 1.5, then
it should work.
You can try different weight values in here
to see how it is performing, And you should
try different weight values here and the CFG
values here, as I have just shown with CFG
scheme.
So you see it is taking two hours to generate
why it will generate combination of these
and batch size 4.
If we calculate we got 12 multiplied by 11
grid, it will produce 12 multiplied by 11
grid and then it in each generation it will
generate 4 images.
So in total it will be a multiplication by,
like this, 528 images and among them you will
be able to understand that.
So this is all for this video.
If you want to support us, you can become
our patron on Patreon.
Please subscribe, like, share and write in
the comments that which what you want to see
next.
And you can also join our official discord
channel from about page of our channel and
just click the official discord channel.
So far, we have 4 patrons.
I thank them very much.
This is keeping us to produce more high quality
videos.
And, as I said, just go to the playlist and
check out the playlist of our stable diffusion.
Everything is in here.
I will also put this video and the next videos
in here as well.
Thank you very much.
Hopefully see you later.