Greetings everyone.
Welcome to the most beginner-friendly and
yet the most advanced and up-to-date Stable
Diffusion DreamBooth model training tutorial.
In this guide video, I am going to use the
latest Automatic1111 web UI and the DreamBooth
extension.
The interface and the features of the DreamBooth
plugin have been significantly changed, so
all other tutorials are now obsolete.
I have been experimenting for over 7 days
to find the best settings and the training
parameters.
Moreover, I tried to learn what each option
does and I have explained everything in this
video.
Before starting, let me provide some quick
info.
Stable Diffusion is a text-to-image generative
public AI model, and the Automatic1111 web
UI is a tool developed by the open source
community to use Stable Diffusion easily.
DreamBooth is an AI algorithm that allows
you to teach new subjects or even styles to
existing Stable Diffusion models very successfully,
such as teaching the face of a person.
In this tutorial, I am going to use freshly
installed Automatic1111 web UI to teach my
face by using Stable Diffusion 1.5 official
version.
I will also show how you can do the same training
on Stable Diffusion version 2.1 as well.
Moreover, I will show you how you can inject
your trained subject, in this case my face,
into any custom model and obtain amazing results.
I will demonstrate an example by using the
very popular and very high-quality custom
model Protogen x3.4.
With this injection methodology, you can use
any namely released custom model and obtain
even better results.
You won't even need to retrain your subject
for this to work.
This method provides such high-quality images
that you cannot even obtain them on paid services
like Lensa or Midjourney.
The Automatic1111 web UI is getting constantly
updated, so let me show you the version I
am using from official repository.
This is the official repository of the Stable
Diffusion web UI.
It has been recently taken down, but it is
now back again.
So if you can't find this URL, just check
out the video and I will update the description
of the video and the comment of the video
so you will find the latest link of the Automatic1111.
So the commit we are using is published 9
hours ago, January 7, 2023.
If you don't know how to install Automatic1111
web UI, I have a great tutorial for that.
So this is the homepage of our YouTube channel.
Go to playlist and in here you will see Stable
Diffusion DreamBooth playlist and in this
playlist, easiest ways to install and run
Stable Diffusion web UI on PC.
I will put the link of this video to the description
and also you can watch how to use Stable Diffusion
version 2.1 and different models in the web
UI.
This is also very important.
I will also put the link of this video to
the description as well.
One more thing.
This is commonly asked.
If you encounter any problem, go to about
page of our channel and in here you will see
our Discord channel link.
As you can see, I am currently hovering that.
You can join our Discord channel and ask me
any questions that you encounter.
So this is our beginning screen of the Stable
Diffusion.
And first let's start with installing our
extension, DreamBooth.
To do that, go to extensions tab, click available
load from and in here you will see DreamBooth
extension.
When you type DreamBooth, it is listed in
here.
I am just clicking install and it is getting
installed.
You should see a message here: OK, it has
been installed.
We have one error, but it is not a problem.
It still works.
So you see, we have a message on CMD window
and also installed into the C web UI tutorial
extensions as the DreamBooth extension.
Now we have to restart CMD window because
we are the first time installing and it is
a necessity.
Otherwise it won't work.
Let's close.
Let's restart.
OK, restart has been completed.
Let's just refresh and then go back to extensions
and check for updates every time you start.
OK, it has been just got updated.
So I'm just clicking apply and restart UI.
OK, it is done.
After the first time installation.
You don't need to restart CMD window once
again.
So you see, this is how frequently this stuff
are getting updated.
Literally, it has been updated just now, as
you can see.
So you should always check the latest version.
Now we can start our tutorial.
We are now.
We see the DreamBooth tab in the interface.
We click that.
This is the interface where you are going
to generate our model and train our face or
new subject.
First of all, we need to generate our model.
You can simply enter any name here.
It doesn't matter.
So I will enter as web UI and the identifier
prompt of my model, which will be ohwx.
I will explain why it will be ohwx.
Then we need to check source point.
You can also import from Hugging Face, but
I don't suggest that it is not necessary.
I am checking version 1.5 Pruned ckpt.
So version 1.5 pruned ckpt available in the
official repository of StableDiffusion 1.5.
You can just download it from here.
Why we are using Pruned ckpt, not the pruned-emaonly
ckpt, because this is better for training
new subjects.
When you click here, you can just download
it with clicking here.
And after you put that into your model folder,
it will be also available here, as you can
see.
OK.
Then just click the create model button.
OK, you see.
We have a message checkpoint successfully
extracted to this folder.
Where it is.
Let me show you.
It is inside Web UI Tutorial.
And let's go to our models and inside DreamBooth,
inside Web UI ohwx and in here working.
And these are actually weights of the model
that we have just composed.
Lets continue.
Now this model is selected here.
This is where the selection we make.
After we make this selection, we will train
the selected model.
Yes.
OK.
Now let's go to the settings tab in here.
First click performance wizard.
It will set the parameters according to the
VRAM of your GPU.
If you have less than 12GB of GPU, it is really
hard to use DreamBooth.
Unfortunately.
You can use LoRA, but it is a topic of another
video.
Actually, it is almost same as this video,
but there is.
There are some just few tricks, and I already
have a video for LoRA.
So after watching this video, if you watch
that video, the LoRA video.
You can easily apply LoRA to your training.
It is in here.
You see how to do Stable Diffusion LoRA training
by using.
I will also put the link of this video to
the description as well.
So training steps per image epochs.
First of all, let me explain what is epoch.
We will have a training data set, the pictures
of the subject that we are going to teach.
In this case, I am going to teach myself.
I will use 12 images of myself.
Therefore, one epoch means that 12 steps.
So each step is a training step and each epoch
is training all of the training images one
time.
So one epoch means 12 steps in my case, because
I have to have training images.
And how many epochs we want?
For teaching faces it is usually suggested
150.
So when you go to the concepts, just click
training with a person.
It will set the most appropriate values for
person.
So you see, now it is set to 150.
However, you can set this as much as you want
and you can use a certain checkpoints.
I will explain that.
So I'm just going to make it 300.
And how much time you want to wait between
each epoch: zero, This is also zero.
OK, this is important.
How frequently we want to save our training.
You know, if your computer crashes, if you
cancel your training, if whatever happens,
you will be able to continue from your latest
saved model.
Therefore, this is important.
Also, if you do over training and you want
to use previous training checkpoint, you also
need to have a save.
So I'm going to set this as 10.
Be careful that when you are doing the DreamBooth
training, it is usually taking about 4 to
5 gigabytes for per saving.
So if you don't have much hard drive space,
you need to set this a higher number perhaps.
This is saving preview images each epoch,
for example, or for whatever the number of
epochs you want.
This doesn't take space, but this will slow
you down.
So I'm just going to leave this as five.
Batch size: Now, this is very important.
If you increase batch size, it will speed
up your training significantly.
However, this will also increase your GPU
memory usage significantly as well.
If you increase these numbers, you need to
increase both of them equally to obtain the
best results.
So now, for example, it will be almost four
times faster.
Also, make sure that your training images
count is divisible to this number.
So two multiplied by two makes four and you
must have training number of images divisible
to four.
So it can be four images, eight images, 12
images, 16 images, 20 images, but it shouldn't
be 17 images.
OK, this is the formula.
Let's say you have 16 gigabytes of GPU RAM,
then you can make this three by three.
And then you should have nine or 18 or 27
or 36 images.
That is the formula.
I'm just going to leave this one by one for
now.
Also, another thing is, if you make this two
and two, like this, it will be four times.
Then you need to also increase learning rate
by four times, like this and this.
Otherwise it will be very slow.
It is also requiring to speed up the learning
rate as well.
As much as you increase them.
Since I will use one by one, I am just going
to leave the default learning rate.
OK, set gradients to none when zeroing.
If you select this, it will increase the GPU
RAM usage.
How can you know that?
The DreamBooth has a wiki pages and in here
they have RAM usage settings.
Let me show you.
OK in here: settings known to use more VRAM.
High batch size, as I just explained.
Setting gradients to none when zeroing, which
is these settings in here.
So when you check this, it will use more VRAM
and then use EMA.
OK.
Now let's continue.
And I will explain.
Gradient checkpoint: This is technique to
reduce memory usage by clearing activations.
So it is good to check it out.
And then we are not just passing here.
These are just kind of more advanced things
to play with it.
After you get used to how to use the DreamBooth,
you can just change them, but in the learning
stage just leave them as they are.
If you set these too high, it will get too
fast trained.
However, it will also over train easily.
If you get them too low, then you may never
get it trained.
So this is kind of experimental thing that
you need to do a lot of experimentation.
Image processing and resolution.
This is important.
When you use a model version based on the
version 1.X, then they are 512 pixels.
If you use version 2.1 then there is also
768 pixels version.
So you need to set this according to the version
of your base model.
OK, the base model, the source checkpoint.
We checked here.
Since we are using version 1.5, official version.
It is 512 pixels.
Don't apply horizontal flip.
This is not good for faces.
Center crop.
If your images are not cropped, you should
check this out.
I will explain how to set your images.
Since my images are center cropped, I am not
checking this.
Sanity sample prompt.
OK, this is important.
We are going to use this prompt to see the
overall training of the model.
But how, in in terms of overtraining or not.
During the training training, I will explain.
So I am going to enter here photo of ohwx
man by Tomer Hanuka.
I will explain why did I enter this prompt.
And by Tomer Hanuka.
You will understand it.
Miscellaneous, pre trained VAE or path.
These are advanced things and you don't need
currently.
OK.
OK, advanced stuff.
This is important.
If you check box the use EMA, then it will
improve your training quality.
However, it also increases the RAM usage significantly.
Use eight bit Adam: This will reduce the RAM
usage.
BF16: This is also.
This will also reduce RAM usage.
xFormers: This will significantly increase
your training speed.
Cache Latent: This will also reduce the VRAM
usage.
All of these are actually written in this
page.
The out of memory top of the wiki.
I will put this into the description.
So you see these are all decreasing the RAM
usage.
Actually, it says that cache Latent increases,
but as far as I know this is not increasing.
But you can test that.
So the Step Ratio of Text Encoder Training.
This will improve your training quality.
However, it will also increase the RAM usage
of the graphic card.
So if you encounter out of memory error, you
should set this zero.
But the optimal value for faces is 0.7, for
style 0.2.
And the other things you don't need to play
with them.
They are more advanced stuff.
OK, now the concepts.
This is the very important part.
You can set a [filewords], prompts and directories.
So first of all we have to set our training
data set.
Training data set directory.
Where are my training data set?
It is inside my pictures folder and it is
in here Best DB.
So all of these images are now 512 by 512
pixels.
Let me show their original version.
So their original version is here.
How did I set them like this?
I have used a Paint .NET to crop them as I
want.
For example.
Let me show you: paint dot net is a free tool,
by the way.
You can install it from the Google.
Just click, like this, and then I am just
cropping them with a square.
So I click rectangle, select, then click here,
then in here, fixed ratio like this, Then
you can pick the any part of the image you
want.
Just for example here.
Then you can control-C control-N and it will
paste into a new place.
You can save it.
Or in here.
You can just resize these to very low resolution
like this, with control-R. It will open resize
type like this, then control-V and expand.
You see, now it is cropped.
Alternatively, you can use Birme .NET.
Birme dot net is a famous site to crop images.
It is commonly used in the community.
You can just, for example, upload any image
there and crop them.
For example, let's upload this image.
These are currently squared, but if they are
not square, it will also automatically let
you square them.
Let me show: OK, you see, both of these images
are not cropped.
So you are able to crop them with your mouse
like this: set the position, then set the
resolution from here: 512, 512.
If you use SD version 2.1, then they will
be seven 768 pixels.
OK, you can also use auto detect image focal
point.
Do not resize.
And you can click here.
If you check, do not resize, It won't.
They won't be resized to this resolution.
Then save a zip and all of them will be saved
as zip.
Then you can extract them with the software
you have.
If you don't have any software like Winrar
Windows still able to extract them.
All right.
If you can't make them, just join Discord
and I will help you, hopefully.
So data set directory.
When you ready your images, then we will enter
the path of it.
So this is my.
Let me enter the folder directory.
I click here and you see I am able to select
the path.
I do control-C to copy it, paste it here (ctrl-v).
So this is the directory where my training
images are located.
Classification directory: Now, what is classification?
Classification are generic images that we
will use to not over train our model and also
keep the inner sanity of the model.
So that the entire model does not become looking
like us.
OK.
So for this I will just generate a new folder.
Yes, I have copy pasted the path.
I will set it as web UI tutorial.
You can also enter an existing another directory.
It is fine.
Instance token: Now [filewords] are used to
set the different description for each training
images.
This is very, very advanced and hard to do.
So I will explain this in the later parts
of the tutorial video.
For now I will just skip them.
You can also skip to that part in the video,
because I will put the sections of the video
into the description.
Now prompts: This is very important.
The instance prompt is used to define the
keyword that will activate our new subject
that we taught to the model.
So in here you have to pick a unique word,
but it has to be very specific and rare.
Whatever you enter to the model.
They will get turned into tokens.
They will split into tokens.
So there is a reddit thread that explains
the rare tokens.
I will put link of this page to the description
and in here the rarity of the tokens are listed.
So, for example, you have entered, let's say,
mill.
It is a single token, but mill probably exist
in the real life a lot.
Therefore, you have to go to the bottom and
try to find rare tokens that you can't make
sense of.
For example, they.
Also, these tokens should be used in other
languages as well.
For example, from here: ohwx is a very famous
token because this is a token that almost
does not exist in anywhere.
When I type ohwx to the Google, you see all
unrelated things.
They look like spam.
So this is a good token and, for example,
you can also try other tokens here that looks
like to you weird.
Maybe this one?
Yes, this, OK.
I'm not sure if this is a real name or not,
so you can verify it, but ohwx works very
well and the token you pick is extremely important.
Because your training will begin from that
token and you can inject a new token that
does not exist in the database, so everything
you enter will become a token that it knows
they will get splint into.
Even if you generate a new keyword, such as
SECourses, the model will not see this as
an SECourses.
How will it see it?
First it will look to S key, SE key.
So the SE key does exist, OK.
Then it will look sec.
So, yes, sec also exists.
And then it will look seco.
OK, there is no seco, so it will get split
into sec.
And then it will be like it will check the
other characters, the remaining characters,
so they will all get split into yes our SECourses
will probably become sec our ses or something
like that.
You see, you are understanding.
I am hoping that.
So the keyword you enter will get split into
tokens, no matter what you enter.
Therefore, we are picking a single token that
is very rare from this list and I have done
many tests.
So ohwx is working very well and then we need
to enter the class of the subject we are going
to teach.
What am I going to teach?
I am going to teach the face of me.
So it's the face of man.
Therefore, I am just entering man.
So this is really important.
It will use the underlying knowledge of man
in the model to learn my face.
Class prompt: now, as I said, this will be
used to keep sanity of our model and prevent
overtraining.
When you also hover it, it says: read me for
more info.
I wonder if they added into the wiki yet.
In the basics perhaps?
OK, in the wiki, in the basics they have a
small explanation.
A class specific prior preservation loss is
also introduced to prevent overfitting and
encourage the generation of diverse instances
of the same class.
They have made an example like this.
So in class prompt I am going to enter photo
of man.
OK, you see, these two are same and the sample
prompt.
This will be used to generate preview images
during the training so we will be able to
see how the training is going on and if it
is becoming too overtrained or not.
So in here I am going to enter photo of ohwx
man.
OK, I am not entering any negative prompts
and I'm not using any sample prompt template.
So these are more, let's say, advanced things
that you can also play with them after you
learned the basics.
And in here, class images per instance.
In the community it is usually said that have
minimal 300 images total.
In the official paper of the DreamBooth.
Which is here.
I will also put the link of this paper to
the description.
They have used 200 classification images.
I have made some tests but I can't say for
sure how much minimum is necessary.
So I am just going to follow the community
and to reach the 300 images I need to enter,
let's easily calculate 300 divided by the
number of training images.
I have 12, so 25..
You can also calculate like this.
So classification, CVG scale.
This is same as text2images CFG scale how
many, how much CFG scale you want to use for
generating classification images?
By the way, you can also use text2image tab
to generate your classification images.
Put them into the folder that we set here.
Then the extension will not generate any new
images.
It is up to you.
You can use the both ways, but if you use
this way, it will also generate a text description
file same as the image name, and it will put
the description you have typed here inside.
That I will show in a moment.
Classification steps.
So this is the number of steps equal to the
in here.
Sampling steps: OK, and number of samples
to generate.
So this is the number of samples that we want
to be generated during the training to see
how the training is going on.
You can set this to 1, 2, 3, 4, whatever you
want.
Sample seed -1.
It means that the every image generated for
samples will be different random with a random
seed and the samples CFG scale 7.5.
You don't need to change this.
These are just same as the text2image.
You will make sense of it after you get used
to text to image.
OK, and now let's return back here: How many
images we want to generate for classification
at the same time in parallel.
So I have 12 GB VRAM memory.
Therefore, I am able to generate 10 images
as a batches, so it will take lesser time
to generate classification images.
By the way, you only need to generate classification
images one time for each class prompt.
So if you don't change photo of man, if you
don't change your subject class, then you
you don't need to generate them once again.
So for showing you, I will just set this as
five and you will understand.
It will generate images, five and five as
batches.
OK.
And one more thing: you can teach up to three
concept at a time to the model.
So the first concept is is: let's say it's
me, and in here I can also teach my wife picture
for example.
It can be like wife DB.
So another folder and its classification data
set can be exactly same as the other one,
or no, it wouldn't be, because it would be
related to women.
Since it will be a woman, not man.
Therefore, let's say woman images, and in
here you need to use another keyword for that.
So it is important to find a rare keyword
from this list.
I don't know which ones are very rare, but
a ske is commonly used at another prompt.
So it can be like a ske woman.
And in here it will be a photo of women and
sample will be a photo of a ske woman.
OK, and the rest is same.
And you can also add another concept here.
But the only thing that matters is the class
of the another subject, If it.
If it is a cat or a dog or a tree, whatever
you are teaching the class and instance prompt
so that you can differently call them and
you can use both of them in a single picture.
For example, you can generate pictures of
your wife and yourself in the same picture,
or your dog and yourself in same picture.
But for this tutorial I am not going to teach
multiple concepts, so it is up to you to teach
or not.
I will just teach a single concept.
All right.
Now we are moving to saving tab.
In here you can enter a custom model name
for saving checkpoints and LoRA models.
You can check out the half-model.
They say that it doesn't decrease the quality,
but the checkpoints are smaller.
I didn't test it so I can't say if it is 100
percent correct or not.
So to keep the quality in max, I won't check
it.
Save checkpoints to sub directory.
You should make this.
You should check this checkbox so that the
savings will be under Web UI ohwx.
They won't get in the same directory.
Now this is important to set.
Generate a ckpt file when saving during training.
If you don't check this, then let's say you
won't be able to test, load back and test
the model at the 20 epoch or 40 epoch or 60
epoch.
So you should check this out.
You can also continue from that point using
that as a base mode.
And you can also load that model and you can
do test inference on that.
So this is important, but this will increase
your hard drive usage.
Be careful with that.
Generate a ckpt file when training completes.
Yes.
Generate a ckpt file when training is canceled.
I'm not checking this because when I cancel
I don't want it to generate a ckpt.
After canceling you can just load the model
and click ckpt and it will generate a ckpt
file from the last saved weights.
Now weights.
You see there is also option to save separate
diffuser snapshots when saving during training.
This option will generate weight files, like
you see here.
So for demonstration purposes I will also
select this from later point you can just
make them as a new model folder and then you
can continue your training from there.
Alternatively, I believe you can generate
a new model from your saved ckpt file as a
new source checkpoint and you can continue
from that saved checkpoint ckpt file.
I think both should be same.
OK.
After you did settings, just click save settings.
When you click train, I think it is automatically
also saving.
Now I will generate the class images before
starting training.
This will use the settings that I did set
in these options.
And let's see what kind of class images we
are going to get.
OK, so you see, it is generating 300 class
images for training.
Why?
Because currently I have no images in here,
but, as you can see, it is not working right
now.
So there is a mistake.
Obviously, To solve this mistake, I will just
restart the application.
OK, restart is completed.
Let's refresh.
Go back to our extensions tab.
Check for updates.
If there is an update.
Yes, there is a new update during the video.
The updates are coming, So let's just refresh.
OK, refreshed.
Let's go back to extensions.
Check for updates.
OK, we are at the last.
Then let's go to DreamBooth, select our model
load settings.
Go to the generate.
Before generating, I will delete these incorrect
images first.
Let me do that.
Go to the pictures and in here, go to the
web UI tutorial.
Ctrl-a shift-delete.
Yes, all deleted.
And just click generate class images.
OK, let's see if any error again.
OK, OK, I think error continues.
So instead of these methods, I will use txt2image
tab to generate images.
The only difference between these and using
text to image is: let me show you.
Meanwhile, just let's restart the application.
When you use, generate images like this will
also generate a text file, same name as the
image name, and inside it it will write photo
of man as a description.
So this is useful when you do [filewords]
training or when you do LoRA training, But
for now it is not necessary for us.
I just reported this bug also to the developer,
so I believe it will get fixed really quickly.
OK, so we are going to generate our class
images from here.
Classification images: photo of man.
I'm just typing that setting the sampling
steps counts 40, setting CFG: 7.5.
So this batch size means that processing multiple
images at the same epoch.
It will use more GPU RAM, but it will make
it faster.
And how many I need?
I need 300.
Therefore, I am going to set this as 38, like
this, and then just click generate.
So now it will generate images.
But make sure that the selected model here
you see, is same as the model that you used
to generate your model.
So in here, when you select your model for
training, it shows the base model source checkpoint.
You see Stable Diffusion 1.5 pruned, and currently
I am generating same images from this model.
So the generated images will be saved in text
to image folder.
Let's open it by clicking here.
OK, when I have clicked open folder in here.
It didn't open because it says in the CMD
window: text to image images does not exist.
After you create an image.
It will be generated because, as I said, this
is a fresh installation to demonstrate you.
Therefore, all of my settings here are also
default.
I didn't change any of them.
And there is one another thing that I want
to mention.
In the DreamBooth model selection You will
see in the SD 1.x versions they has they have
EMA or not.
So if they have EMA, it will increase your
further training, fine tuning the model.
So you should pick EMA version having models.
It only exists in the 1.x versions.
I think in the SD 2.0.
In the 2.1 there is no model released with
has EMA features.
OK, the first batch has been completed.
Let's open the folder.
Now the folder is opened.
So these are photo of man.
You see, there will be very weird images,
bad quality images, but they don't matter
much.
They are not very important as long as they
are generated by our checkpoint model.
OK, after all of the images have been generated,
just select them all with control-C, then
go back to your folder where you want to get
them saved web UI tutorial.
I am just going to copy paste them in the
folder.
OK, let's return back to our DreamBooth and
load settings.
So now we have the sufficient amount of classification
images.
Now we are ready to click start training.
OK, when we start training, it will first
start by caching them out.
We will see that.
So you see, it says that it has found 300
regularization images.
Therefore, it is not going to generate any
more images.
Currently it is caching them.
OK, after the caching has been completed,
you will see the training has been started.
It is progressing step by step.
You see 13, 14.
If you get out of memory error, then you need
to try further decreasing memory usage.
All of the low memory settings and high memory
settings are stated in the wiki.
I will put this into the description.
Also, you are seeing right now.
High batch size, set gradients.
These will increase your memory usage and
these will decrease your memory usage.
There is not much else things that you can
do, and one another thing is that the developers
are constantly trying to optimize and improve
the extension to reduce memory usage.
So therefore, when you watch this video, or
maybe one month later, you, your card, could
perhaps do use DreamBooth training.
So that's another possibility.
And after how many steps we are going to see
our first sample images?
We can calculate it easily.
In the settings tab.
We did set as 10 epoch and how many training
images we have.
We have 12, you see in here.
Therefore, after 120 steps we are going to
see our first sample training sample images.
Actually, on, after 120 steps, it will save
the checkpoint.
After 60 steps, because we did set 5 epochs.
We are going to see the first sample image
and 60 steps has been completed.
So it is generating preview images at the
step 60.
Ok, the first samples have been generated.
Let's open the samples folder.
So where they were saved, they were saved
under our model.
Let me show: Ok, I have so many same tabs.
Ok, inside our installation folder, go to
the models and in here go to the DreamBooth
and in here you see the same name as our training
model name.
Enter there.
In here you will see samples.
When you click here you will see the samples.
So the first sample is generated with this
sample prompt with ohwx man.
So this is our class and this is the unique
instance prompt we have set.
Ok, so there is another image.
You see.
This is generated with photo of ohwx man by
Tomer Hanuka.
Why did I set this and where did I set this?
I did set this in here.
If you remember, The second prompt you see
in here with name it as one, is the sanity
sample prompt.
The number here is the step count that it
has been generated, and this is the other
thing is the prompt used to generate it.
After we progress in the training, you will
understand why we are using this.
As much as this image looks like us, with
a different style, it means that our model
is learning good, and when it becomes exactly
like us, not styled like this, that would
mean that our model is overtrained and now
we can't apply styles.
Our aim is learning our teaching our shape,
but not overtraining it, not distributing,
disturbing the underlying context, the knowledge
of it, not overriding it completely.
So after we progress in the training, we will
understand better.
Okay, now let me explain to you to how to
prepare your training dataset images.
What is important with the selection of the
images?
What we want to teach is the subject that
we want to teach.
The most important part.
I want to teach my face.
Therefore, other than my face, everything
must be different, or, let's say, should be
different in each of the images.
So, other than face, what can be different?
My clothes and the background can be different.
So if you are teaching your face other than
your face, all of the backgrounds and the
clothes should be different as much as possible.
As you can see in my pictures, I have made
sure that all of the backgrounds and the clothes
are different or the clothes are not visible.
So if you make your clothes different and
your backgrounds are different, then the model
will learn your face, not your clothes or
not the backgrounds.
That is what we want.
We want to teach our face, not the other things
in the pictures.
If you use same clothes, then the model will
not say that this is the face and this is
the clothes and the model will learn both
of them at the same time and it will reduce
your stylizing your face.
Therefore, the key point of preparing training
images is having different things other than
the subject.
So if the subject is face, the other things
must be different.
Also, you should have different angles of
photos and different distances of photos.
It will make the model learn different angles
and different distances to generate different
kinds of different styles, more variety of
images.
So if you make your images, I can't say my
data set is the best available data set.
You can expand your data set with more variety
of images, more variety of poses, more variety
of angles, more variety of lightning.
Lightning also matters.
It would be better.
However, this is a small data set and I think
it is working pretty decently.
But if you expand this data set, your training
data set, with more variety, then it is better.
It will learn your face or subject in a more
generalized matter and with that way we will
be able to produce different kind of different
artistic images more easily.
Okay, so you see, currently it is compiling
a checkpoint ckpt file and you can just load
the ckpt file directly and do inference on
that checkpoint.
It is compiling checkpoint at the step 360,
which is epoch 30, and so where are these
checkpoint files are located?
They are located on models inside inside our
folder, and you see the ckpt file and the
yaml file is here.
If you don't know what are yaml files, just
watch my how to use Stable Diffusion 2.1 and
different models in the web ui tutorial video.
I will put the link as usual, and let's check
out our so far samples.
So in this image this is like me, but no other
sample prompts are like us.
We just need to do more training.
And also in this screen you will see 5.5 or
3.7.
So this means that this is how many iterations
per iteration is done in each second.
However, these values are not very correctly
displayed, so there is also loss and this
lr is important.
This shows your learning rate.
So 2e-6, what does that mean?
That means that it is a number.
When you type it to the google 2e-6 and go
to the first result, for example, it will
show you it is equal to this number.
Okay, so this is the number.
Actually we did set in our settings, in our
learning rate, you see.
So this is equivalent of the scientific e-notation
number.
If you set changing numbers from here you
see there are changing numbers like polynomial,
constant or other things, learning rates then
you will see different numbers in here and
it also shows the gpu usage.
However, this is also not very accurate.
It says that 9.5 gigabytes currently is being
used.
Okay, okay, it has been 72, 82 epochs.
Now i will show you how you can continue training,
if an error occurs.
So to illustrate that, i will just crash the
application with closing here.
When you close from here, it won't save any
checkpoint or anything.
Use the error connection error.
Then just restart the application and after
the restart is done, just refresh your interface.
Go to the DreamBooth tab, select the model,
click load settings it actually it will be
automatically loaded.
And then just click train.
It will continue from the last checkpoint,
which is 80 epochs.
Let's wait.
Okay, you see it has.
It is continuing from wherever it is left,
as you can see here.
Also, in the cmd window it shows first resume
epoch, and first resume step, step, as you,
as you can see here.
Okay, we are over 168 epochs and we are already
doing a lot of over training.
How do i know?
As i said you in the beginning, i have entered
a sanity, sanity prompt.
So the samples numbered with, dash one are
the sanity prompts.
And let's look at the sanity prompts changes.
So the sanity prompts started like this.
Then in here you see, the sanity prompt is
resembling me and also here resembling me,
okay, resembling me somehow.
And after certain point, actually after 1368
steps, the sanity prompts become just like
me.
You see, it is not anymore styled okay, like
this, like this and this is almost as like
me, and you see, they are not anymore styled
like here.
Styling is completely gone and in here.
Therefore, now we are sure that we are doing
over training.
So i am just going to stop training with cancel
and i am going to use different checkpoints,
test them out to see how they are performing.
Now the hard part is coming: the prompting,
the proper, the correct prompting to obtain
the good results.
So the training has been cancelled.
Let's look for the closest one.
I am refreshing here and in here, yes, this
one looks like the closest one: 1308.
Then go to the text2image tab.
So how are we going to generate our own image?
We are going to use photo of.
These two keywords are also associated with
us right now, but not as strong as our prompt
instance.
Ohwx and man.
Also man is very much associated, okay, so
when we type like this and hit the generate
button, it will generate our own image.
Okay, the image is ready.
You see, it is like us and now we need to
style it.
So let's add in this name style and let's
see what kind of result we are going to get.
Okay, as you can see, we didn't get much of
styling, so therefore, i am going to show
you an extension which is named as web ui
prompt generator.
You can install it from available tab.
Just click load and in here just search for
prompt and you will see prompt generator and
just click install and then just apply and
restart the ui.
After that you will see prompt generator tab
here.
So let's get some extra additional keywords
from prompt generator and let's click generate.
Okay, there are a lot of results here, but,
this came to me, could work like, so i copied
it and pasted it in here and let's see the
result we are going to get.
Okay, we got somewhat decent results, but
it is still not very much like us.
Therefore, we need to increase the prompt
strength.
So what is prompt strength?
prompt attention.
This is from the official wiki of the Automatic1111.
So if you want to increase attention to a
word by factor of 1.1, you can take the word
inside one parentheses.
If you want to increase the attention even
more by factor of 1.2, 21, so you can just
put like this: alternatively, you can use
an easier way, which will be: let me show
me, let me also zoom in, just type like this:
okay, so this will increase the attention.
This will force model to generate image that
is more like us and it will going to ignore
the rest.
Also, in this prompt there are so many things
that would be unrelated to disney style.
So what would be related to disney style,
for example, CGI, and let's also add some
other keywords.
Okay, here are results.
Not very much like us and not very good quality.
We need to improve the prompt with adding
some negative prompts as well.
Okay, here i have added some negative prompts
and now you see we have a much better artwork,
but still not very much resembling to me.
So i am going to try another prompt with also
increasing, the, the emphasis of our unique
keyword, which is ohwx and the man.
In every prompt you must have ohwx man with
some increased strength, probably to get your
own face, and also adding photo of.
Why?
Because during the training we have used class
prompt as photo of man.
Therefore, now these three keywords are also
associated with us, but the most association
is coming from ohwx, okay.
Okay, so i am going to try with emphasis of
1.5 and a new prompt like this.
Let's see the results.
Okay, we got an image that is not very stylized.
Therefore, we need to increase CFG.
So what is CFG?
CFG is classifier free guidance scale how
strongly the image should conform the prompt.
Lower values produce more creative results.
We want the model to obey our prompt because
we are providing a very detailed prompt.
Therefore, we need to increase scale and try
it.
So i will show you how you can try multiple
scale values.
Go to the bottom on here and go to the x/y
plot.
So in the x/y plot there are x and y values.
Currently we only need x value.
In the x value i am going to select CFG scale
and in here i am just typing seven, eight,
nine, ten, eleven, twelve, thirteen, fourteen,
fifteen, sixteen, and i wanted to use same
seed for all of the input so that i can see
the changes, and i will generate four images
in each iteration, in each step.
My graphic card is able to process four images.
If you don't have much vram, you can't do
that.
Then you should increase this.
Okay, if you check this, keep minus one for
seeds.
Then each image in the each generation would
be different.
However, i want to see the difference of CFG
effect in a legend.
Therefore, i'm keeping it like this and then
just click generate.
So currently, in the CMD window, actually
it is generating four images at each epoch.
So you see, in the 20 steps, actually it is
processing 80 steps.
So four of them is being parallelly processed,
since i did set batch size to four.
Okay, CFG images.
Different CFG images have been generated.
I have modified the input because the previous
input was not very good.
Actually, it turns out that.
But it is not important, because when you
are working with Stable Diffusion, you have
to make, you have to generate a lot of images
to find out the good ones that you, you would
like to obtain.
So let's look at, look at the effect of the
CFG.
So this is our seed value.
If you use this seed value, you will always
generate similar images in each generation,
as long as you keep the same value, same model.
So this is the CFG scale seven.
At the CFG scale seven, there is not much
resemblance.
At the CFG scale eight, a little bit resemblance.
Look at how the images are changing.
This is CFG scale nine.
There is some resemblance in these two.
Okay, and if in the CFG scale 10.
Now, this is also some resembles and in here,
okay, you see, resembles is increasing and
in the CFG scale 14 actually, there is really
good resemblance in this image and in this
image actually, and so it goes, and after
certain CFG scale it becomes, i think the
quality starts to be decreasing.
So therefore the CFG scale makes difference.
Now let's say you want to test out different
artists, styles with different CFG scales.
How can you do that?
I am putting here a special keyword that i
am going to use by replace kw.
Okay, then the rest is anything you want,
and in the bottom so this time i am going
to select prompt sr.
Okay, so the prompt sr works as separate a
list of words with commas, and the first word
will be used as a keyword.
Script will search for this word in the prompt
and replace it with others.
So these keywords will be replaced whatever
i type here.
So let's say wlob and then artgerm and then
whatever other artists that you want to test.
Okay, i have added two more artists, so we
have four artists.
Let's also test 4 CFG values 10, 11, 12 and
13.
Perhaps let's start from 11, okay, and let's
keep seeds for minus one, but that time we
we couldn't test the CFG or the style.
Therefore, let's keep the same seed, okay,
and you see, there are restore faces, tiling
and high res fix, so you could also pick them
to improve your output, but that would take
extra time and you can do them in the extras
tab which i will show.
And the batch count is one and batch size
is four.
Let's see what kind of results we are going
to get.
By the way, these other keywords will also
heavily affect the artist style.
Therefore, if you want to only check out the
artist style, then you should reduce number
of extra keywords here and let's see what
we are going to get.
Okay, i did get runtime error.
Why?
Because i have forgotten to put this keyword
in here.
The first keyword has to be that.
Now i need to run again.
Okay, now the generation started.
You should always, check out the CMD window
and what is happening here.
If you get an error, then you should fix it,
obviously.
Okay, this is the kind of tile that we are
going to get.
Actually, it is pretty useful.
So, you see, in the top CFG scale and in the
left we got the art style, by the way: It
also produces results with: replacekw and
not much like representing the style or me.
Therefore, perhaps we can remove many of the
keywords that would take away the style like:
let me do.
Okay this time we have more kind of styling,
as you can see here: this is the default,
this is wlobe, this is artgerm.
This is Robert S Duncanson and this is Karol
Bak.
Especially Karol Bak style is pretty different
and significant, as you can see.
So the key point here is is, with Stable Diffusion,
that you have to generate a lot of images,
and some of them will be very, very good and
maybe majority of them will not be good and
useful.
This is the nature of the AI based art generation,
especially if you are trying to generate art
based on your subject, a new subject, and
also when we were doing training in here,
you can use more classification images.
That can help.
I said that the community is using 300 total,
but that is not a hard limit.
You can just use 200 images for per training
image and that may help you to improve your
style.
Actually, it is also the number used in the
official paper, as i said.
So it is up to you.
You have to do experimenting.
The numbers and the quality you get also totally
will depend on your training data set.
If you get a much variety having a training
data set, as i have explained, then your model
can learn much better.
I will show you one another thing here.
There is a prompt matrix that will generate
combination of the images.
Okay, so when you type your query like this
and select it from matrix, this query will
become face photo of ohwx man:1.3, like this.
And then they will get combined by like this.
So this will be generate all of the combinations
of the written text separated with the let
me tell you once again, vertical pipe character.
It will generate all of these keywords combination
like this.
Okay, i will show one another thing.
Let's say you are going to sleep and you want
your computer to generate many different style
of images for you during your sleep.
For that i will show you an easy way to do
it.
So our first our first prompt is face photo
of ohwx and let's say 1.4.
Then let's add some certain keywords to get
some certain kind of prompt.
Okay, i have typed like this and generated
20 input like this, then it has generated
me a lot of results.
I am going to copy all of this into a notepad
file, paste it so you see they are actually
copied as one line each one.
Then i will generate several more.
Okay, i keep copy, pasting the newly generated
input to there.
Okay, now i have 60 lines of inputs like this.
I am going to save it as.
Let's go to the pictures and nightly prompts.
Okay, then go back to text2img tab and in
here select prompts from file or text box.
You can paste all of them here or you can
upload them from here.
So i will upload them, from the text box,
from the text file, and they are all uploaded.
I am going to say, use random seed for all
lines, because i want to get as many as possibly
different results.
And then i want to generate how many images
you want to generate for each one.
I want to generate, let's say, eight images
in parallel, and currently they will use the
CFG value I am going to set here 14.
So with 60 and 8 images batch size, we are
going to get 480 images.
Let's say you want to generate 4000 or whatever
you want.
So if i set this 20, we are going to get exactly
20 times multiplied by 8 and multiplied by
the number of lines we have.
9600 images during the night with a lot of
different inputs, variation, and among them
you can pick whatever you want and use it
as you want.
This is one of the options that you can.
Okay, after i click it, it started generating
images.
For example, generated this one, and if you
wonder what is this image, you go to the png
info and then you can just go to get the image,
drag and drop it in here and it will show
you all of the parameters it has.
So this is the prompt input and this is the
negative prompt input it has and the number
of steps used.
The sampler used, the CFG scale used, the
seed, so with this seed you can repeat this
image generated.
You can use this seed and change the CFG value
and generate other variations of this and
the size and the model hash.
The model hash, of course, will change since,
we are using our custom trained model.
The batch size and the batch position, so
this is also important.
To exactly get this, you need to generate
a against batch size as 8, and the sixth position
will be this one.
If you use this seed and this CFG value and
this sampler.
We are getting some decent photos, and i will
leave it to run during my sleep and tomorrow
i will show you, of course, in a moment for
you.
We are going to see what kind of good images
we got.
Okay, here you see, some of the images i have
generated during my sleep.
They are pretty good quality, but they are
very similar.
Why?
Because it appears that the inputs i have
used to generate them were not much different.
However, some of them are really high quality.
For example, this image: you see, it has almost
perfect eyes, perfect shape.
It's a really good quality image.
So your training data set and the keywords,
the prompts you use, will hundred percent
affect the outcome that you are going to get,
and you really need to stylize your prompt
according to what you want to get.
Now let me show you a few of the prompts used
for generating these images.
To doing that, i am going png info, okay,
and then i will drag and drop.
For example, let's first see a 3d like image.
Okay, and you see this used blender, zbrush,
autodesk maya, unreal engine, colored, because
if you want to generate a 3d like image then
you need to use these kind of keywords.
Then you can send these to.
For example, let's go to the extras tab.
In extras tab i can upscale this image to
get it a bigger size.
After my testing i have found that R-ESRGAN
4x+ works best.
There is also anime version.
Also, LDSR is working very good, but this
requires a lot of gpu memory.
So when i click generate, when the first time
you generate it, it is going to download the
model that is necessary for R-ESRGAN 4x+.
You can see here and now we will see the upscaled
image.
So this is the upscaled image.
The upscale and the original will not be exactly
same, but let's compare them okay.
Let's make them, not zoomed in, okay.
So you see, both of these are, really similar.
A little bit loss of quality.
Let's also try with the anime version.
Okay, now we got anime version.
So let's say, you want to make your images
like anime, then you can use that.
This is extremely useful.
You can also upscale entire folder.
For example, i will just ctrl a select all,
then i will drag and drop them here.
All of them is now here.
Now i can upscale all of them at once.
Let me show.
During the operation you will see they are
getting tiled like this to generate bigger
size images.
The results of upscaling the extras tab actually
will be inside another folder.
When i click it, you will see they are getting
here and all of these images are now upscaled.
For example, let's open this: this is a pixar
style image, actually.
Okay, this is another pixar style image, so,
for example, this is also another pixar style
image, as you can see.
I have trained these on the Google Colab and
now i will show you how you can upload your
model to the Google Colab and generate images
there with faster than probably your gpu,
because the Google Colab gpu is really strong,
able to process a lot of images at once in
a parallel way.
Okay, you see, all of these are getting upscaled,
okay, um, let's see some of them like this,
as you can see, okay, okay.
Now i will show one another cool thing.
Usually you may not get very good looking
eyes or some errors in the face, and there
is a very good way to improve the eyes or
the overall structure of the face.
It uses another AI model and let's try this
image improving.
Usually, the my images were really good eyes.
Okay, to test it.
I am just going to not upscale, but i am going
to use GFPGAN.
So this GFPGAN is a model to improve the eyes.
Let's test it.
When the first time you use it, it will download
the necessary model.
Okay, now let's compare the result.
This is the original image and this is the
fixed image.
Now let's also apply an upscale, okay.
Okay, after applying upscale and applying
a GFPGAN, you see it is now looking much better
in terms of quality correctness.
This will seriously improve the eyes.
Let's open them like this.
Okay, let's zoom in.
So you see the difference is huge: much better
quality, styling.
You can apply this to your generated images
as a batch as well.
Just go to batch process and select the options
from here and it will do everything.
You can also try these other options.
I didn't find them very useful actually, and
there is also not a description to them.
Okay, now i will show you how you can continue
training from any checkpoint that you did
set.
Just go to the search checkpoint and you will
see your saved checkpoints here, by the way,
to get them saved in the saving, you need
to check this generator ckpt file when saving
during checkpoint and then, if you generate
a new model from that checkpoint, you will
basically continue training from that certain
checkpoint.
Now i will show you how you can use these
ckpt files directly in a Google Colab.
If you have watched my previous video about
transform yourself into a stunning ai avatar,
this tutorial is how to do training on a Google
Colab and, everything is explained there to
use your ckpt file in a Google Colab.
It is so, so easy.
First we are going to generate a new model
from the our wanted checkpoint.
That let's say i want to use step 1380 as
a checkpoint.
Then i am giving it a name as a Colab image.
Okay, and nothing else.
Just click create model.
Okay, it has generated a, generated a new
model for the Colab image and inside working
directory you just need to upload this into
google google drive and then just give its
path.
So for i will say that, my image.
Okay.
Let's say, let's also add our keyword to that
and let's move them inside here and then go
to your drive folder like this, where you
are running your DreamBooth or the Stable
Diffusion, then drag and drop this directory
here.
It will upload all of the files, as you can
see in here.
Once the upload is completed, all we need
to do is changing model path in the inference
tab of the Google Colab notebook.
This is linked in the description of the tutorial.
So you need to change it like this: content:
drive my drive, and in here my drive image
ohwx, which is the folder name that i have
given and i am uploading to the main folder
of my Google Drive.
Then, in the Google Colab, you will be able
to use your trained ckpt file right away.
So what if?
If you want to teach another face?
Just generate a new model like this and this
time, in the concepts folder, set the directory
and the classification directory for your
new subject.
However, be careful with something.
Currently, my model is trained with ohwx man
as an instance prompt and photo of man as
class prompt.
So if i am going to teach another, a person,
a male, then i have to pick another keyword,
for example ske or another rare keyword, and
um, it will teach this man into the model
as well.
So we will be able to use both of them.
However, probably you will get mixed results
because man keyword were already taught for
my own image and when i introduce another
man image they will get mixed.
So it could be a problem, but you can try
it.
Test it and if you generate sufficient of
images, then i think you will.
You can obtain still good results.
However, if you inject some another class,
like a woman, then it shouldn't be much problem
and you should be able to teach multiple different
subjects easily.
Now i will explain more advanced stuff.
For example, the directories, data set directory.
Okay to be able to use [filewords], you need
to have a training data set named like this:
okay.
So for each image, you are also going to have
a text file with the same name.
The extension will be txt, like this, and,
you need to write the description of that
file properly.
There is a new AI model for captioning images.
This is not implemented to Automatic1111 yet,
but i will it will be.
I will put the link of this into the description.
You can also locally run this.
And if you don't know how to locally run run
this, then you need to watch our this video
on our channel.
In this video, i am explaining how to locally
run HuggingFace files.
Okay, and i will just use the online demo
right now because it is not very much used.
So, first image, i will just drag and drop
here.
Sorry about that.
Okay, like this: and click submit.
It will generate the description for this
image.
You see, you should use the caption generated
by GIT large.
This is the best one.
A man with dark hair and glasses is smiling.
Okay, so let's just change this text text.
Text description, like this.
However, there is one key issue: you have
to have your class for this image inside this
description.
So my class is man and therefore it is there.
Okay, let's go.
Then.
This is another image that we want to caption,
so let's submit it.
Okay, and then another image description is
here.
Let's open the description: a cat with long
whiskers looking at the camera.
And this is the class of cat, and it is inside
here as well.
Yes, correct, and the rest will be for dog
as well.
Now for classification images.
You need to do the same.
When you generate classification, you also
need to have classification image and its
description.
Let's say: this is my classification image
and it is it is generated with photo of man.
Therefore, i need to generate a same file
description like this and inside here i need
to type photo of man.
When this tab get fixed, let me show you maybe
it is already fixed, i am not sure.
In here, you see, we have generate class images
and when you use that feature, it will be
able to: let's try it, actually okay.
And let's yeah, it doesn't matter, okay.
And when we type class prompt here photo of
man, i think it will generate with it.
Let's try it, okay, it is not working.
It says maybe say okay, it's still not working.
When this become working, then you can easily
generate it.
Or you need to generate the description like
this: photo of man, and it will generate images
like that, or photo of cat or photo of dog.
So this will be your classification directory
with description like this and this will be
your classification directory with naming
like this.
With this way, you can teach multiple subjects
in the one run and you can also possibly improve
your training quality if you provide a better
description with defining more things.
By the way, when defining, you should specify
your subject in the description what you want
to teach.
If you want to teach face, then you should
describe the face in mostly.
Okay, and one another thing: okay, once you
prepared your folders.
Now here the way to do it.
First of all, we are defining the data set
directory as usual.
Okay, let's set it.
And let's also set the classification directory
like this.
And in [filewords], we need to use defining
prompt instance.
Okay, this will be used to define it.
It has to be a single word.
Therefore, i am entering ohwx and the class
token.
This will be also a single word.
By the way, it won't be very precise actually
if you use this way, class token.
But yeah, looks like if you teach multiple
different classes, then you may not get very
good performance, for example, teaching a
cat, a face, a cat, a dog and a man, because
they are conflicting with the current setup.
So using three concept is better, but let
me also explain it to you.
So this will be man.
And in prompts you are just going to type
[filewords] and class prompt.
You are just going to type [filewords] and
leave blank to use instance prompt optionally.
Use [filewords] to base sample captions on
instance images.
You can just also use [filewords] to see what
is what it is generating.
This is called mixed where in the basics of
the wiki of DreamBooth extension.
So you see there is DreamBooth regular training
that i have shown in this tutorial.
Then there is fine tuning.
Fine tuning is the standard approach for big
data sets.
Only the captions of the images are used.
[filewords] class images are not used.
These results in a model that doesn't need
instance token and reacts to any prompt.
So in this case you are overall training.
What does that mean?
That means that, let's say, in your [filewords]
you have cars, you have cats, you have dogs,
you have men.
You are training all of these words.
And this is how the custom models you see
are usually trained.
Let me show an example.
So, for example, protogen x3.4 is a custom
model and it is working pretty good.
How did they train it?
They probably trained it with fine tuning.
So in fine tuning they have, precisely prepared
the descriptions of each training image.
They didn't use any classification images
and they have overall changed the underlying
context, data, the knowledge of the model.
So when you use now man, it produces quality
of man images depending on their new fine-tuned
data set or car or castle or whatever that
you are improving your model on.
And there is hybrid.
Okay, actually i said mix it, but it will
be hybrid.
Hybrid, for lack or of better term, is achieved
using instance token in combination to [filewords]
as instance prompt.
Trained Dataset will be linked to that instance
token.
This minimize the bleed but requires token
in every prompt, as you can see here.
So you have to use or ohwx french bulldog
or ohwx, whatever you have teached.
Also you see the class token is person.
So with hybrid model with [filewords] if you,
if you don't do fine tuning but only teach
any subject, the subject should be, i think,
same class.
They can't be from different classes.
So you can teach multiple person in a single
run, maybe 10 person, with just providing
correct [filewords] and their descriptions.
So for this person you need to add, let's
say a man personA.
Okay, this will define personA.
For person b, you need to add personB and
for person c, you need that personC.
But you are not going to add into this description:
you are not going to add this instance token.
Okay, you don't need to type instance token
into the [filewords], into the description
of the training images or the into the description
of the classification images.
Okay, this is important.
Okay, now i will show how you can understand
out of memory error.
So it is easy.
I'm just going to load settings for our existing
data set.
You see, i have an error.
So it looks like i had error in cmd.
I just need to restart.
Okay, i did restart and in the settings, if
i set use EMA.
So actually this improves our result quality
but it costs more ram.
And then i just click train and let's see
how we are going to get out of memory error.
Okay, we got our error.
Let me show you how to understand out of memory
error.
You will see runtime CUDA out of memory.
If you are seeing this error, all other messages
are not important.
This means that with the current settings
that you are trying to training, your graphic
card is not enough and you need to reduce
the ram usage.
Now let me show you all of the settings to
how to reduce the ram usage.
Okay, so for minimal ram usage you need to
pick LoRA with the LoRA.
There is just a little bit difference.
It is only different when you try to do inference
and generate new images from generated LoRA
file.
And when you watch this video you will learn
that, okay, LoRA will significantly reduce
ram usage.
Other than that, always make sure that your
batch size and gradient accumulation steps
are one and other than that, in the advanced
tab you need to pick use 8 bit adam and select
bf16 and select xformers.
So for xformers to be able to, you need to
set your starting arguments to xformers and
minus minus no half.
These will allow you to use that.
Cache latents.
Actually, this is the.
This is still not clear.
You should try both this checked and unchecked.
Because some says that this increases, some
says that this decreases . So also, Step Ratio
of Text Encoder Training.
This should be zero because this increases
quality but also reduces, also increases the
vram usage.
And other than these, there is not much else
that you can do.
These are the lowest possible.
Also, you need to uncheck this checkbox and
you need to check this checkbox.
So when you check this checkbox it will increase
your vram usage, but when you check this checkbox
it will reduce your vram usage.
Actually, actually, the settings are written
in the troubleshooting part of the DreamBooth
wiki extension, in the OOM tab, and there
is also overtraining and other things.
Actually, overtraining is still in working
process and i have already shown you how to
understand overtraining.
And one another cool thing that i am going
to show you is preprocessing your images.
So with preprocessing images you can easily
generate descriptions for your both training
images and your classification images.
Of course they won't be very accurate, so
let me show you.
I am picking my best db 512 as source directory
and the description directory will be same.
So in here you can even define their target
resolution, change them, but i prefer manually
changing them and captioning.
So for captioning, i am just going to select
ignore, so it will generate new captions and
i am going to use deepbooru for captioning.
You can also generate flipped copies oversized
images, splitted, autofocal point crop.
So let's say you have tens of thousands of
images, then these options will be extremely
useful for you.
However, if you are only going to train your
face, then you should manually prepare your
training data set to be best, and then i am
going to generate captions for them.
I am just going to click preprocess.
It shouldn't change the width and height because
they are already 512 pixels and it is downloading
the deepbooru for captioning.
This is another model, just as i have shown
you in here.
The deepbooru is not as good as caption generated
by git large, but it is still useful and in
a moment we are going to see.
Okay, it has thrown an error.
Says that same director specified as source
and destination directory.
Obviously, this is not allowed.
Actually, it's a good thing that they don't
allow.
So i'm just going to change it as processed,
so that you don't override your original images
and just lets click preprocess.
Okay, the models are only downloaded one time,
and all images are preprocessed.
So let's check out the preprocessed images.
Okay, you see same images with descriptions.
Let's look at the description.
So the description is one: boy, black hair,
facial hair, gray pants, jacket, long sleeves,
male focus pants, realistic solo sub stable
track jacket and track it track pants.
So it's a pretty good description.
You can also manually modify them.
Let's also modify our classification images
so that, it will generate all of the description
of classification images.
By the way, this is useful, as i said, when
you use [filewords].
If you are not using [filewords], then these
won't get used.
This is also useful, very useful, if you use
a hyper network or embeddings, and i will
also hopefully make a video about embeddings.
Hyper networks are not very good, but embeddings
are really really good.
Okay, let's preprocess our classification
folder.
So the preprocess is in train tab.
This is a feature of Automatic1111.
Okay, and preprocess it.
It is also pretty fast.
So this will be extremely useful to caption.
And also, if your images are not properly
cropped and you have tons of thousands of
images, as i said, that will take huge time.
You can just use this.
As a beginner you can also use this to make
your job easier and see the results, how it
is performing.
Let's say you picked your hundreds of images
of yourself and you don't want to spend time.
Then you can preprocess images like this and
try, try, train, try the training on them
and see the results.
If you can get good results, then why not
spend much time, more time on them?
But if you want to get perfect results, then
you need to manually crop your images and
set your set your description.
So let's see the preprocess now.
Every image has description.
Let's look at them.
Okay, it, for example, it defined this man
as a girl, which is a very incorrect and also
3d asian black shirt.
Okay, this is a completely incorrect description,
as you can see.
It's completely failed.
And now let's compare this with the large
git which i have shown.
Okay, i wonder what kind of result we are
going to get with large git, so i'm just going
to drag and drop.
By the way, as i said, i have suggested adding
this model to the Automatic1111 to get better
results, and the large git generated a portrait
of man with beard.
Yes, absolutely fantastically correct when
compared to this trashy description, as you
can see.
Okay, as a final thing, i suggest you to look
at the ELI5 training.
So this is getting updated by the experienced
persons and, for example, in [filewords],
they say that they are giving an example of
instance, token alexa is bad because underlying
data for alexa is great and it would be hard
to override it.
This is also bad because this is getting split
into like this: ohwx, great.
Class token is also important.
I already experienced them, but you can also
check these pages.
I will put the links of these pages into the
description.
Now i will show you one another very cool
thing.
You see, this Protogen x3.4 is a custom model
that has been generated by using multiple
models, a lot of training, and you see, if
you train your face or subject into this model,
it won't produce good results.
Because the underlying data have been significantly
changed.
So how can we inject our face into this model?
There is a way to do that and now i am going
to show you.
We go to the checkpoint merger and in the
primary model we are selecting our target
model, which is Protogen x 3.4.
Secondary model will be the model that we
train it we are using, which will be this
one: ohwx 1308.
And there is tertiary model.
So the tertiary model will be version 1.5.
This is the model, this is the base model
of our model, and what we are going to do
is we are going to extract our image from
base model and we will apply our image into
the our new target model.
Let's give it a name: ohwx, protogen okay,
3.4, and set the weight 0.75.
This is 75%.
You may ask: how did you come up with this
value?
I asked the community and, according to the
experience of the community, 75% is a good
point.
You can, of course, try multiple different
points.
You can try your different checkpoints to
see how you perform.
Also, click the add difference.
So this will extract our face information
from our base model and it will inject our
face information into our new target model
without breaking the underlying context, the
information.
We are going to generate ckpt add difference
and just click run.
In the cmd window you will see the messages
like this: and checkpoint saved, then refresh
here and just go to our new model, which is
ohwx protogen.
Now we can produce images by using the protogen
model and our face, same as usual.
Okay, everyone, i have done a few tests and
the results are just amazing.
So you see, these are some of the images that
i have selected from the results.
And let me show you something.
So you see, this is generated by protogen
and this is my original, real image.
And this is the generated image.
You see the quality.
It is just amazing.
And what kind of test i did.
For testing, i have used the x/y plot, i have
entered different x values as CFG and i have
entered prompt sr as the weights.
So how did i make?
So you you see the ohwx man and then we are
entering a weight here, right to give an importance
to it.
So i have entered a keyword here change weight
and i have used it as a change weight here
in the prompt sr.
So the you the Automatic1111 ui into application
changed the weight for me and tested different
weights.
Now i can see the properties of this generated
part particular image to see what were the
used values.
Then, based on that, i can generate anything
i want.
So the weight used was 1.4 and the cfg scale
was 8.
So by using 1.4 and cfg scale 8 i can generate
much more quality images.
So these two parameters will work with my
merged model.
By the way, i also have used something else.
You see, there is a model hash and that hash,
the hash written here, also displayed here.
This 95 means that i have generated another
checkpoint, but this time i have used 95%
weight.
This worked better for me.
So in the beginning you can start with 75
and if you are not getting good images then
you can increase it and make different model
merges and then do test on them.
So this is the way how to test and find out
the good working parameters for your model
and then use those parameters to generate
more stylized images as you want.
But the results are just simply amazing.
You can't just get these results so easily
on the default Stable Diffusion model.
So you can inject your trained model, trained
face, into any custom model out there and
generate the beautiful images as you want.
So let's also upscale this image.
To do that, i am just going to send it to
extras and i will upscale it with R-ESRGAN
4x+.
And here the result: it is just beautiful.
Let's also apply GFPGAN to get better face
quality.
Okay, now, amazing, as you can see, amazing
quality, amazing image.
There is only only an artefact here, as you
can see, . So if i would generate such images,
i could also get rid of this artefact.
I think i have covered pretty much everything.
As i said in the beginning, just join our
discord channel.
From our about page and also in the in here
you will see the link.
Just click the official discord . Please also
share, like, subscribe, and if you support
us on our patreon, i would be greatly appreciated.
Currently we have three patrons.
I think i thank a lot to them for becoming
patron of our, supporting our job.
You can also join our channel and support
us from here, as you can see.
I would appreciate every bit of your support.
Hopefully see you in another video.
Please leave comments and ask the questions.
Ask the topics that you want to see as a new
um tutorial.
Thank you very much.
Hopefully see you later.