Greetings everyone. Welcome to the
most beginner friendly guide for how to
do training on Stable Diffusion
models by using automatic1111 web UI.
In this tutorial I will train portrait images
of my brother by using Low-Rank Adaptation,
as known as LoRA training method on the
stable diffusion 2.1 768 pixels model.
If you do not have prior knowledge, please
watch these two videos on our channel.
On our channel, go to the
playlist section and in here
you see we have stable
diffusion dreamboot playlist
And in here first watch easiest way to install
and run stable diffusion web UI on PC.
So this will teach you how to install
web UI on PC and how to run it.
And then watch how to use stable diffusion version
2.1 and different models in the web UI.
This will teach you how to download and install
different models and use them with the web UI.
After that, you are ready to watch
this tutorial and follow me.
To be able to train with LoRA,
you need to go to the extensions
tab here and install DreamBooth
extension, check for updates.
And if you don't know how to
install from available, first go
to available tab, load from
and in here search DreamBooth.
Since I am currently hiding extension
with installed it is not showing.
But when I disable it, you see DreamBooth
is already installed but it has updates.
So I am going to update it.
OK, so for updating, we just
click apply and restart UI and it updates.
Now, when we check for updates, you
see we have the latest version.
And, as I said, for installation,
go to available.
And when I check this installed, it shows
the DreamBooth is here and click install.
OK, that's all it.
After that, and after you
restart your application, you may
need to do a full restart
for DreamBooth tab to appear.
You will get this tab.
OK, and once you are in here and from the
models, you have the version 2.1.
You are ready to follow me.
You see, current stable diffusion
checkpoint is 2.1.
OK, first of all, before starting our training,
we need to prepare our images.
Since I am going to use 768 pixels version,
I need to set my images as 768 pixels.
So my images are inside in this folder.
I didn't still set their resolution.
So first I will show you
how you can crop them with
an open source, a free software: Paint .NET.
Let me show you Paint .NET.
OK, this is the Paint .NET and you can download
paint dot net from its official website in here.
It's an open source .NET
based software.
Alternatively, you can use this website, which
is free to resize and crop your images.
But I prefer Paint .NET.
I will show how to crop one of the images.
So I am going to drag and drop
this image into here.
Click open.
And in here you see there
is rectangle select,
and in here I click fixed ratio.
I set it one hundred and
one hundred, like this.
Then I am selecting the image
like this as I want.
I click ctrl-C to copy, I
click ctrl-R for resize.
I am typing something smaller
and clicking enter.
Then I am clicking ctrl-V expanding.
Then I am clicking ctrl-R again to resize.
And I am exactly resizing as 768 pixels.
Then I save it with one hundred
percent quality.
You can also use PNG or JPG images.
Alternatively, you can use
Birme dot net as well.
However, you may not trust this website.
It is up to you.
So I will select two images
from here, upload them.
And in here I am going to select 768
pixels like this: 768 pixels.
OK, and you can just set where
you want cut to be like this.
Then you need to click save as zip.
It will download a zip like this.
You can click it and you can then extract them
into your folder and overwrite existing files
And they will be exactly as.
Let me show you 768 pixels.
I will open with paint, not net,
And you see they are 768 pixels.
So this is the way you need
to prepare your images.
OK, all images are cropped by
768 pixels and 768 pixels.
Now we are ready to do training.
So go to our stable diffusion web UI.
So you may wonder what is LoRA?
LoRA is a low-rank adaptation for faster
text to image diffusion fine tuning.
It uses both UNET and CLIP.
It is faster than DreamBooth.
Also, its checkpoints are much smaller
than the full checkpoint of DreamBooth.
When you do a checkpoint with DreamBooth,
it generates full .ckpt file.
However, LoRA generates much smaller files.
And when you are done, you can generate the
full checkpoint file. To do training
we go to the DreamBooth tab here and we
first need to generate our model.
I am going to use my brother.
I need to select the source checkpoint.
I have selected version 2.1 like this:
I am using the EMA version and
I am not going to click this.
This is not necessary.
OK, and just click Create button.
After you click Create button,
you see it is downloading
the necessary files from the internet like this.
So you need to wait this download.
If you are not seeing anything on
the web UI, always check the running
command line window to see
what is happening like this:
OK, the model has been generated.
You see checkpoint successfully extracted
to Models DreamBooth my brother working.
We can also check it from
our installed folder.
Let's go to C drive and I have
installed in StableDiffusion
web UI, in Models and in here in StableDiffusion.
And now no, not in StableDiffusion in
DreamBooth folder, and in here you see there
is working directory and there is my
brother directory, as you can see.
OK, let's return back to our interface.
In here you see there is LoRA Weight.
So this defines what percentage of LoRA
Weight should be applied to the UNET
when training or creating a checkpoint,
and it is same for Text Weight.
Setting this as 1 may cause
overtraining, over tuning.
However, since we are going to do generate
our portrait images, our own portrait
images, and we are just teaching
one face, this is fine for now.
You can pick this half model.
It will enable FP16 Precision, which results in a
smaller checkpoint with minimal loss in quality.
But we don't need this for LoRA, since
the checkpoints are already low size.
And when you click this,
checkpoints will be saved to
a subdirectory in the selected checkpoints folder.
So I am going to click training
wizard person.
OK, and let's set up our parameters.
This is really important.
So how many training steps we
want to do for each image?
How many images do I have?
I have images. Let me show
once again: total: 16.
OK, since I am going to compare checkpoints
quality, I am going to set this very high because
I will early terminate the training or I will
decide whether I have trained enough or not.
OK, I am setting max training
steps as zero, pause after
an epochs zero, amount of
time passed between epochs.
By the way, one epoch equal to 16
steps because I have 16 images.
OK, and I am not going to set
any with pause between epochs.
So use lifetime steps, epochs when saving.
Let's say you have stopped or paused your training
and then later at a time you continue it.
So use lifetime means that it will consider your
previous training epochs steps as well.
However, if you unclick
this, it will use only this
session of training steps and epochs when saving.
So I am just unclicking it.
This is really important.
The save checkpoint frequency
by n steps.
OK, since I didn't click this,
it will check by n steps.
Since I have 16 images. If I set this 16, it
will save checkpoint after each epoch.
OK, if it is confusing for you, you can just
click this and you can set this 10.
So it will save checkpoints
every 10 epochs.
In this case, since I have 16 images,
it will be after 160 training steps.
OK, this is fine.
I will also save a preview of
the image after each checkpoint
so that I can decide whether
that checkpoint is good or not.
I will explain this in the video,
so don't worry about that,
You will understand it.
Batch size:
OK, how many images to process process
at once per training step?
We are going to process one image
per training step and we will do
same for classifier regularization
images to generate at once.
If you have more than one GPU, you can increase
batch size to process them in parallel
I suppose. Learning rate and other rates.
I am not going to touch them, but you can try to
obtain better learning rates or encoder rates.
You can also scale the learning rate, but
I am just leaving them as default.
OK, image processing:
This is important.
Since I am using 768 pixel version,
I am setting it as 768.
However, if you use another version, like version
1.5, in that case you need to use 512 pixels.
So this resolution depends on your Stable
Diffusion model, version and type.
I am not going to do any cropping since
I have cropped. Apply horizontal flip.
It means that the images will be flipped as well,
so it will add more variation to your images.
You can set this.
Do we have pretrained VAE Name or Path?
No, we don't have.
We will use the base model vae.
When you watch my previous videos, you will
learn what is vae and how to set them.
OK, concept list:
I am not going to use any
concept list as well, since I am
just going to train for
teaching one portrait image.
And advanced tab:
OK, this is important.
This is where we set our
training methodology.
We are going to use LoRA methodology.
So use 8bit Adam.
This is, enable this to save VRAM.
If your graphic card VRAM is
not much or let's say you have
encountered not enough VRAM
problem while training,
you can set this.
I am going to set this for now because I'm
not sure how much VRAM it is going to take.
And you can also set FP 16.
So, mixed precision.
You probably want this to be FP16.
If using Xformers. You definitely
want this to be FP 16.
And if you have watched my previous
videos, you know that we are
already using Xformers to speed
up our inference and training.
So I am going to set this.
Memory Attention:
I am going to set this Xformers.
My graphic card is RTX 3060
and it supports that.
OK, Don't Cache Latents:
When I hover my mouse over
that, you see, there appears a
tooltip and explains to me what
does that checkbox is doing.
When this box is checked, latents
will not be cached.
When latents are not caged, you will save
a bit of VRAM but train slightly slower.
So for a lower VRAM usage,
I am checking this.
Train Text Encode. Enabling
this will provide better
results and editability but cost more VRAM.
Yes, we are setting this.
I am not changing any
of default parameters
And I am not changing these
parameters as well.
So we are done with parameters tab.
By the way, I will make
this arbitrarily high number
because I will stop it
myself. The training myself.
OK, concepts.
This is really important.
This is the part where we are
setting what to teach.
OK, maximum training steps is minus one.
It will never end.
OK, data set directory. Path to the
directory with input images.
So to get the director of my
input images. I am right clicking
one of the image, right clicking
properties, left clicking.
And in here you see it shows location.
I am copying this like this.
Alternatively, you can also click the search
bar here and select entire path and copy.
And I am pasting it here.
Classification data set directory.
OK, this is a path to directly with classification
regularization images.
So let's also set a path for this
to understand what is it.
So, however, you shouldn't set them
inside here because in that case
it is using, I think, all of the
images in all of the folders.
So let's say, brother
classification folder.
OK, let's enter here.
Copy the path like this.
File words: OK, we are not going to
use any file words in this training
because we are not training hypernet,
or let me show you what was it.
It is embedding.
Therefore, you can just leave this empty.
But prompts: this is where we need
to enter a unique prompt to teach
the face of or the other thing
that we want to teach to the model.
So I will give it a unique
name as my brother.
OK, like this, you can
give any unique name.
It should be unique enough that it won't
be in the original training data set.
So to be sure, you can just also expand
it like this. Class Prompt. Now
this is important.
What am I teaching to the model?
I am teaching face of a man.
So I will say face of a man.
OK, like this. Classification
image, negative prompt.
OK, you may give a negative prompt to generate
better quality classification images.
These images will be generated to
improve your training success.
They will be automatically generated.
So let's enter a good
negative prompt here.
OK, I have a decent negative prompt
I have prepared previously.
I have used a chatGPT to expand some
of the famous negative prompts.
I will put this into the comment
section of the video.
So, don't worry, you will be
able to copy and paste it.
So I'm copying and pasted in here.
So I will explain to you
what is this as well.
So this class prompt and classification
images what are they?
Sample Image Prompt.
This is important
Why?
Because during the training we want to
see how the training is going on.
And for that we will generate
sample images.
So the sample images will be like this:
First we will give the
instance prompt so that we will
be able to see the face of
the person we are teaching.
Then you can append here some of the good
keywords to obtain better results.
But if you just want to see
how much the model has learned,
you can leave this only with the instance prompt.
So you will get a better idea of how much
the face has been learned by the model.
Sample prompt template.
We don't need a prompt template right now.
Sample image: negative prompt.
You can just copy and paste
it in here as well.
Okay, Image Generation.
So when doing training we will generate,
let's say, generic images, generic
face of a man, images to make
our training more generalized.
Okay, to improve its success rate.
So I will generate 10 times
of the my input like this.
And these are for the other things
that you need to set for generating
template images, we may say,
or generic images, we may say.
Number of samples to generate one.
Okay, it looks good.
Okay, you can just enter 10 times of it.
It's up to you.
And we are ready to do training.
But I will also show you one
other thing in settings. In settings
when you go to training section here, you can
reduce VRAM usage by clicking this checkbox.
Okay, I think it will probably
reduce your training speed.
And you can also turn on pin
memory for data loader. Make
training slightly faster
but increase memory usage.
So you may play with these settings to obtain
the best possible training speed.
I have 12 GB VRAM.
So I may open this, but I won't open that.
Also. Yeah, the others are just fine.
Okay, and let's click training
button, since we are ready.
Okay, when we click training button, first it will
generate the generic face of a man images.
Why face of a man?
Because we have entered our class prompt as
face of a man and where they will be saved.
I think they will save it in
here brother classification.
So it is starting to generate our generic face
images to add more variety to our data set.
So you see, it is generating face of
a man with the given prompt I have.
You can also improve this prompt
with adding other, let's say,
styling prompts, more quality
prompts, anything you want.
If you watch my previous videos on the channel, on
the playlist, you will understand what I mean.
This is actually same as doing inference text2img
from here to generate images.
It is exactly doing that to improve variety
of our classification training.
You see they are really
bad quality right now,
So maybe we should tune our class prompt.
To do that I will just cancel the training
with clicking cancel button.
You see training cancelled. And you see that
these are the images it has generated.
I will modify. I have deleted all of them.
I will modify the class prompt
by adding some keywords.
Okay, to decide what to enter,
I have moved to text2image tab
and I have typed: portrait photo
of a man, HDR, 8K and sharp.
The keywords that you will find from
real photos of people. And I have entered
my negative prompt as well and this
is the image that has been generated.
It is pretty good.
So I am returning back to my DreamBooth
tab and in here I am changing
to my the class prompt like this
and now I am clicking train again.
Now it will generate 160 class
images for training.
Basically the generic images to
improve my training quality.
Let's see what kind of results
we are going to get.
We should get results same as we got
in text2image tab actually.
Yeah, it's a decent face photo of a male.
Why we are doing this? As I said,
to increase the variance variation.
When you have different styles,
different variations of photos.
It will prevent over training
and it will force model
to learn face of the person
that you want to teach.
OK, so you see, now we are getting
really decent quality face images
of male persons and it will
help our model to learn better.
OK, meanwhile, the training is going on.
I mean, the image generation is going on.
Let's quickly recap.
First, we generated our
model with a unique name like
this, and we have selected the source checkpoint.
You can source checkpoint any model on
the Internet that you want to teach.
OK, it will work. Exactly
same as version 2.1.
The only thing that may differ
if your model is based on stable
diffusion 1.5 or 1.4, they
use 512 pixel size images.
Therefore, the only thing that you need to change
is the image size, which is where was it?
Let me show you. Here image
processing resolution.
So, if you use a checkpoint model
based on 1.5, 1.4 or 512 pixel based
2.x version, then you need
to change this to 512 pixel.
But if you are using 2.1 version
based model which has native
768 pixel resolution, then
you need to change that.
Other than that, we are going to parameters:
training steps per image.
I have set this very big number because I will
stop the training myself at a certain point.
I will show you when I will stop it and
how I will decide to stop training,
And this is important. I will save and
generate images every 10 epoch.
Every 10 epoch means that
one epoch will happen when
it process all of the images
in my training folder.
I have 16 images in my training
folder, which is here.
It will also put, I think, flipped images
there, so it will be 32 images.
We will see that when training
starts, currently still generating
the generic images that I
have requested, like this.
OK, so I will be able to decide
whether model has learned enough
so that I can stop and start
using the model or not.
OK, so these save previews and save checkpoints is
really important to see the progress of training.
The batch size is, I think, related to
how many GPUs you have, or if you have
a very strong GPU that can process in
parallel two images at the same time.
If it has enough VRAM memory,
you can also increase this.
But if your graphic card can
only process one image at
a time, then you should
leave both of these as one.
I didn't change any of the learning rates or
other things. I did leave them default.
I have also applied horizontal flip
randomly. Decide to flip images horizontally
so that it will add more variation
to the learning data set.
I don't have any VAE or concept list.
I am using LoRA because with this way it
will use lesser VRAM than DreamBooth.
And the save files will be 1000 times
lesser than the DreamBooth, because
Dreamboot generates full size
model files for checkpoints.
However, this will generate minimal
files. Then from those files, after we
are satisfied with the training
process, we will generate full model.
I am using 8bit Adam to save
VRAM. I am using mixed precision
memory attention and I didn't
change any other parameters.
And in the concepts I did
set my data set directory
and the classification data set directory.
I have already shown you them.
We are not using any file words
because we are not doing a
general concept training.
It is not the context of this
video. I may make another
video to train hypernet or textual embeddings.
The instance prompt. This
is really important because
this keyword is being taught to our model.
So when I do inference with the
new model, the tuned model, it will
know that this keyword is the
face of my brother pictures.
Therefore, this is really
important. This is the generic
class prompt. I already have explained that.
And these are the arbitrary numbers.
Actually, this is the arbitrary
number I have entered. I
didn't change the other things.
These are only affecting the
images generated in here.
None other than that. So this part is
only important for these images.
So it will generate 160 images in this
folder. You see, it is also generating
same named text files and it is
saving the description of the input.
You could also modify these
descriptions, but I think
it is not very important for LoRA training.
It is important for hypernetwork and
especially for text embeddings.
Now I will pause video until the image generation
has been done and the training has started.
OK, meanwhile, the class image generation:
So far, we are almost at 50 percent.
It says there is still 20
minutes remaining. Approximately.
It is using 95 percent of my GPU.
It is using almost 9 gigabytes of my GPU
and it is using about 20 percent of CPU.
So these are the values that it is using
for just class image generation.
And let's see how much it
will use for training.
And the class image generation
speed is 14.58 seconds / IT.
OK, the training process has started.
After generating all of the images.
Let me show you them. Once you
have generated these generic
images, you don't have to
generate them once again.
You can stop and restart training and
use these base generic images.
However, an error occurred. So my web interface
is not getting updated anymore,
unfortunately. But the training
is going on, as you can see.
Currently it is two iterations, actually
two seconds per iteration as a speed.
It has done 145 iterations so far.
And let's see how much VRAM. Oh, you
see, my entire VRAM is almost full.
It says that there is
allocated and reserved, but I
am seeing the full VRAM usage in my graphic card.
And after 10 epochs we are supposed to
get our first training output to see.
OK, it says that you see, LoRA
weights successfully saved
to C stable diffusion web UI, which is my folder.
Inside models LoRA. So let's go there and check it
out. In stable diffusion web UI in models in LoRA.
OK, so you see, this is the checkpoint file it
has generated and it is only three megabytes.
So I can generate checkpoint
file for even every epoch.
However, if we were using DreamBooth
instead of the LoRA, this would
be minimal, like 5 gigabytes
or 6 gigabytes or 4 gigabytes
based on the model that you are using
as the first initial checkpoint.
So for version 2.1, it would
be equal to minimum five
gigabytes because the base
model is five gigabytes.
If we were using DreamBooth instead of LoRA,
our every checkpoint would be five gigabytes.
But now we are only getting
three megabytes checkpoint.
It is even smaller than
1/1000.
OK, so we should also got the first
image output of our training.
So where it is saved, If
you are wondering, I think
inside DreamBooth, in my
brother's in here samples.
Yes, So this is the first sample image it has
generated after ten epochs. In this folder,
as the time passes we are going to see images that
will be similar to my brother's sample images.
Let me show you our training
data set images.
Let me show you once again.
So once we get images as close as possible to our
training data set, then we will, we will, we will
generate a checkpoint model file, full model
file, from that file. Which file from the file?
Let me open once again the C folder to explain
better. In here in models in LoRA.
So once we got a good image we are going
to you see the file name is 160.
We are going to get the same file in here and
we will generate a full model checkpoint from
that and then we will be able to generate
the images of the person we train it for.
OK, so now I will pause video until
we got some good results.
Oh, by the way, it seems
like. Yes, yes, the process
has stopped. So therefore I have to continue.
Probably an error has occurred.
Yeah, an error occurred.
So what we need to do is: OK, let me
show you to continue from there.
So I am refreshing the web interface.
This error may occur time to time
And in here I go back to the DreamBooth.
And in here you see, let's refresh.
We have my brother as LoRA model.
And OK, so let's click load params
and see if it will load.
I hope it loads.
OK, it says loading.
I maybe need to restart the application.
Yeah, probably I need to
restart the application.
You see, when you play with the web UI while
training, these kind of errors may occur.
So I will now restart the application.
OK, after I close the command line,
you see connection error occurred.
So let's go back to our stable
diffusion web UI.
Click web UI webui-user.bat.
OK, I have restarted the web UI.
Now refresh and go to the
DreamBooth and pick the LoRA model.
And let's click load params.
Please specify model to load.
So you see, my brother model
is now here. After restart,
and after I click load params,
load loaded config and I
click train, it should
continue from where it is left.
OK, you see, it is getting. Concept
requires 160 images.
It has loaded the same images, so it is not
regenerating the classification images,
It is loading the weights where
it is left, I think.
So the number of examples: 16. Number
of batches per epoch: 16..
Correct.
Number of epochs: one million. As we have set,
the total optimization step is 16 million.
OK, everything looks correct.
And, yes, it is now continuing
where it is left.
This is great.
So if an error occurs, this is how you
are going to continue your training.
So you can further optimize your model
from any checkpoint. And in here,
if you see, let me zoom in.
You see, OK, I did zoom too much. Training
step is 23. This is the current session.
And, you see, this is
the lifetime session.
So this is different that
you are setting in here.
Use lifetime steps, epochs when saving.
We didn't check that.
So we are only taking into
account the current session
steps for saving and previewing the checkpoints.
But this is the lifetime. OK, now
I will pause the video again.
OK, so you see, after the second save
and now it continue to do training.
So sometimes errors may happen,
even though they shouldn't.
So if an error happens, just restart application,
just as I have shown, and continue to training.
So the samples are getting produced.
I hope it doesn't take too much time to
teach my brother face into the model.
OK, it has been only 30
epochs so far and we already
got somewhat similar picture in the third one.
You see, this is the thirty epoch
after 480 steps in total.
And this is my brother.
You see, there is a similarity,
as you can see.
OK, I have noticed another mistake.
You see the command line interface
is displaying the LoRA weights
has been saved to my brother,
underline 160 dot PT.
However, it is correctly
saving in the folder.
So this printed message is incorrect, but the same
with file names are correct, as you can see.
So this is the thirty epoch has been done
actually for. Actually for the epochs,
Yes, since we have 16 images, when you
divide this 16, it is 40 epochs.
And these are the so far generated images.
You see it starts to resemble more
and more as the training continue.
OK, it has been over 1423 steps so far.
So the training step speed is, for
1.60 seconds for per iteration.
So far it is going on.
We are getting closer to our target
image, as you can see here.
OK,
It has been over 5600 steps so
far, which makes 350 epochs.
And for this tutorial I am now going to cancel
the training and I will generate a checkpoint
based on the best that comes to me as best
epoch number, which is sample 2400.
You can continue to do training until
you are satisfied with the results.
But these results are just a preview of
what it has learned. With a good prompt
you can obtain much better photos.
And also it also depends on
your data set quality.
If you prepare better images than in this example,
you can still obtain better results.
I think this is a decent one.
And let's generate our model checkpoint.
So how we are going to generate our
model checkpoint to use later.
You see there is a LoRA model and now we are
going to generate checkpoint from our 2400.
I am entering the model name
here that I want to give.
Let's say, my brother test one, and
I am clicking generate ckpt file.
OK, it is generating.
You can see that it is
loading LoRA from the selected
checkpoint from here and applying weight.
As you can see here: LoRA weight:
What percentage of LoRA weight should be applied
to the UNET when training or creating checkpoint.
Applying the text weight as well.
And then it is saving.
However, the saved file
name is not correct.
You see, it has appended the
latest training number,
However it has loaded 2400.
So I think there is a simple
mistake in the web UI.
So where it is saved,
It is saved inside stable
diffusion installation folder,
then models, then stable diffusion folder.
OK, I am going to rename this
into the name that I want.
Let's say LoRA.
And you see it also has YAML file
and it has to be the same name.
OK, I did rename with F2.
OK, now I can do text2img and generate
new images based on our training.
How we are going to do that:
First click refresh here and then
my new model has appeared here.
It is now loading.
You can see the loading from
this command window here:
Loading config and loading
other parameters.
OK, the model has been loaded.
Now what is the prompt that
we are going to do?
The prompt we are going to do is the prompt we
have given in here, which is my brother face.
OK, this is our unique keyword.
And then we will append the
other keywords that we want.
Even though our model has learned
the face very good
As soon as we add new keywords to
improve and obtain different styles
of the learned face, it totally
produces different images.
Unfortunately, no matter how many times I
have tried, my all attempts have failed.
It always produces different faces,
not the face it has learned.
If I only give my prompt instance, yes,
it produces the face of my brother.
But then what is the purpose of training?
Because I am not able to modify it. Change
the style, produce different styles.
Therefore, now I will do another
training with SD version 1.5.
And let's see the difference between SD version
2.1 and 1.5 when we are doing face training.
Since SD version 1.5 requires 512 pixel
resolution, I am recutting the images,
as you can see. I am cropping them again
And I have removed some
of the very old images.
Actually, I only removed two of them.
Okay, it is like this that I am setting up
the images for SD version 1.5 training.
Okay, yes, like this.
Save as zip and open the downloaded file
and extract them into the folder.
Okay, here, like this, I will overwrite
and the training set is now ready.
Okay, for 1.5, I am first
changing model into 1.5.
Then I am going to the reboot.
And in here we are going
to generate a new model.
Let's say, okay, brother,
SD 15, like this.
And the source checkpoint will be 1.5
because we are starting a new model.
Let's generate the model like this:
Okay, it is preparing the
model file for training.
Actually, everything is same.
Then I am clicking training wizard person.
It will set the parameters.
Oh, I think I click it.
Yeah, I didn't wait process to finish.
Okay, now I will set again.
Okay, now it is set and
the model is also set.
All right, you see, the model has
arrived here for training.
Okay, I am just doing the same things.
By the way, we now need to recompose new class
images for improving the test accuracy.
Also, this apply: horizontal flip
means that on the runtime it will
sometimes provide the horizontally
flipped images in the training.
Okay, it won't generate new
images on the folder,
It will do that on the runtime.
Okay, I am selecting LoRA.
I am using 8bit adam with FP16, xFormers.
Don't Cache Latents.
Okay, I am not changing other things
because it is already learning good,
but we weren't able to generate good images.
I think it was due to version,
SD version 2.1.
Okay, the path for our VAE
here. And classification.
We now need to make new classification,
so I will just make another folder too.
Okay, like this:
Let's enter here.
All right, we are leaving this empty because
we are only teaching one phase.
I will give the same name as the
model name to instance prompt.
Now class prompt.
This is important to decide class prompt.
Now I will do a few tests here.
Okay, with a simple prompt, such
as face photo of a man: 8K HDR,
smooth, sharp focus and
cinematography, we got decent faces.
So this will be our class prompt.
Okay, let's go back to our DreamBooth training,
and the class prompt will be like this:
Classification image, negative prompt.
So let's also copy and paste it.
By the way, don't worry, I will
provide these as comments.
Okay, so the sample image prompt
will be same as before.
Okay, and should I provide negative
image prompt for sample?
Yes, let's also provide it.
Okay, how many we want?
This time? We have how many
images in the folder?
Let's check it out
Once again. Okay, we have 14,
so I will generate just 140.
Okay, I'm not touching this.
Parameters are set.
Everything looking good.
Okay, let's start another training.
So you see, since we don't
have any concept images now, it
is going to generate first
our class images, as before.
But this time we are using 512 pixel
resolution. This is really important because
our base model is now version 1.5 and it
is using 512 pixel as native resolution.
Generating class images are now much faster, you
see, because it is now lower size in dimension.
Okay so, the classification training
set has been completed and now
the training has started and so
far we are at the 50 training step.
You see, it is much faster now
than before because we are simply
working with 0.44, which means
44% of image size than before.
Because before we were
working on 768 pixels.
Now we are working with 512 pixels.
Therefore, it is more than
two times faster.
New model training checkpoints are also getting
saved under the models LoRA folder.
As you can see here with the
name that I have given.
Also, the new folder under
DreamBooth has been generated
for the new training in here, brother SD15.
And in here we can see the
samples it is generating:
so far, nothing resembling at all.
Okay so the training has been completed.
I let it run during the
night while I was sleeping,
so generated so many checkpoints.
And now I am going to use
this particular checkpoint
to generate our .ckpt file from here.
As usual, as previously same.
I have selected the model
entered, selected the checkpoint,
given a name, and then
click it generate ckpt file.
Then now I am going to load
newly generated ckpt file.
So to do that, just click refresh.
And it should come.
And yes, it is.
It has arrived. With now checkpointing
that model.
It is done.
And now we can do our tests.
OK, I have generated over
600 images and some of them
are really good and really resembling the face
we teach it.
So the key thing is that you
need to generate more images with
LoRA because I think it is
not as precise as DreamBooth.
The prompt I
have used is portrait photo of brother SD
15, which is my prompt instance, with weight 1.2.
1.2 weight means that it will give
more importance to this keyword. On the
official page of automatic 1111
stable diffusion web UI wiki features,
You can see attention
emphasis and it is explaining
that how you can give more attention to each word.
You can also use parentheses like this, or
you can directly set importance like this.
So it is totally up to you
to use the either way.
So I have given more importance
to the prompt instance
and I have also written photo of brother SD 15.
And then I have used a
generic keywords to generate
images as close as to our prompt instance.
You see 8K HDR, smooth,
sharp focus cinematic.
I am going to share all these
keywords in the comments of the
video, and I have also entered
a lengthy negative prompt.
I have used Eular a as a
sampling method with 25 steps
and the native resolution for SD 1.5 512 pixels.
So how can you generate
more than 100 images?
Set the batch count to 100,
then go to bottom. Here.
You will see the script
section. By default
it is set to none, but you
can go to prompts from file or
text box and you can just
copy and paste your prompt.
So it will read each line and
will continue generating images
until all of the lines are executed.
With this way, you can generate
much more images.
Also, there are other options
that you can do here.
For example, you can do X and Y plots.
So you can give X values and
Y values and, if you wonder
what they are, separate values
for X axis, using commas.
You can play with these to, for example, generate
different style images with having, let's say,
artist names or style names in your X values and
the Y values would be like your regular prompt.
Okay, so I have selected few of the images and
now I will show you how to upscale them.
The resemblance rate is not as good
as DreamBooth, unfortunately.
So you can also do DreamBooth training.
The only thing different in DreamBooth
training than the LoRA is in the advanced
setup. You just don't pick this LoRA
and it will do DreamBooth training.
And also be careful that when you
are DreamBooth training it will
generate 5GB files, 4GB files,
at the each save checkpoint.
So you may want to reduce this, increase the save
checkpoint frequency, not just 10, but maybe 50.
It totally depends on your
hardware hard drive.
Okay, so what am I going to do is first
let's check out the PNG info.
Tap in here in pictures and
in brother selected.
Let's pick one of them.
So you see Web UI embeds the meta
information of the parameters.
So if you can get the original image
that is generated by the Web UI,
you can just use PNG info to extract
the parameters from that image.
And the one another thing I am
going to show you is extras.
In extras, let's first
try a single image.
You can upscale it.
Okay, the best upscaling algorithm
I have found is R-ESRGAN 4x+.
I pretty much like this. And let's
upscale to 3X dimension.
The first time you do. It may
download something in here.
Since I have done it previously, it didn't
download the necessary models.
Okay, the upscaling is done.
As you can see, now this
is upscaled version.
You can also apply GFPGAN visibility.
The GFPGAN will improve
the face of a human.
It is another model.
Let's do that and see the difference.
Okay, it is getting done.
And yes, so now you see it
is more like a real human.
This is fixing eyes much better,
making the eyes much better
if they are not oriented, if
they are not symmetric.
So you may want to apply this
as well, if you want.
And also you can do batch processing.
For batch processing, just open the folder
with Ctrl-A, select all, open.
It will be loaded like this.
Then it will apply all of the parameters
you set here and click generate.
And all of the images will
be generated as a batch.
So the results of the batch generation
will be saved in a folder.
If you want to open that folder, just
click this folder image here.
You see open images output directory and the
batch processing results will appear here.
You can just directly copy them, paste
them and do whatever you want.
Okay, this is all for today.
Please ask any questions that you might
have. To improve the performance
so I suggest you to use DreamBooth
instead of the LoRA training.
Also, you can improve your data set.
The data set, our data set,
was not that very good.
You see almost same time captured,
same pose images.
So if you add more variety to your data set,
you will obtain better results, more likely.
And also, please like, share and subscribe
our channel if you have enjoyed.
And if you support us on Patreon
we would appreciate very much.
Currently, so far, we have one
Patreon, as you can see.
Thank you very much to our beloved
Patreon, by the way,
And I am hoping that you
will support us as well.
Hopefully, more videos, more advanced videos
will come for Stable Diffusion.
If you want to also learn something about
stable diffusion, let me know by comments.
And hopefully I will make
videos about them.
Hopefully, see you in another video.