Greetings everyone.
In this video, I am going to show you how
you can install, run and use famous Stable
Diffusion web UI developed by Automatic1111
with two different ways.
The first way I am going to show is using
an open source installer exe just like in
traditional applications we install.
The second way will be manual installation
of the web UI.
This exe is developed by one of the Stable
Diffusion community members Leo Mozoloa as
can be seen here, this is his profile.
Usually I do not trust any exes, however,
this one is an open source application and
you can compile it from the source code.
You can also check all of the source code
on the GitHub repository.
This link I will put it in the description
of the video and we can go inside the folders
and see each one of the code it contains.
Therefore in this case, we can trust it.
So let's begin with downloading the installer
exe.
So where do we download it?
We download it from the releases.
The releases are displayed at the right as
you can see here with my mouse.
When I click it, I can see all of the releases.
Just click the exe and it will start downloading.
By the way, you may get a message like this.
This exe is not commonly downloaded and may
be dangerous.
If you see that just right click here and
click.
Keep OK.
After the download has been completed, just
go to your downloads folder.
Right click the exe and run as administrator.
It is important to run as administrator because
this exe will download and install files.
Don't worry about that because it is hosted
on the GitHub repository.
Also this application is now pinned by moderators
of the stable diffusion community and also
I have compiled myself this exe by using advanced
installer application and I have verified
it.
This application you can also download trial
and try, but it is not necessary for you.
OK, now this is the installer exe beginning
screen.
We need to install Python and this exe will
do that as well.
So you see there is GIT and Python.
I click next.
It will do everything automatically for us.
If you encounter any problem during following
this tutorial, please go to our page YouTube
page.
Click about and here you will see our Discord
channel.
Just click it and join our Discord channel
and ask me any questions, any problems that
you encounter.
The Python installation may take some time,
so be patient with that.
OK, so the Python installation and the git
installation has been completed, so there
are several options.
You should pick clean install if you are going
to override your existing or previous install.
You should also click this box.
Install SD checkpoint 1.5, version 1.5 and
the newest vae.
These are, I am explaining what are these
in our another video.
So if you are wondering what are these version
1.5 and new vae you can go to our channel.
Click playlist and in here you will see stable
diffusion dreambooth click that playlist and
in here you see we have how to use SD 2.1
custom models on Google Colab or we have how
to use stable diffusion 2.1 and different
models in Web UI.
This video actually will explain to you a
lot regarding what are these.
OK, so now I am going to pick the folder where
I want to install.
I want to install it inside my C drive.
So I am clicking the three dots here to pick
the folder.
I am clicking C and in here I am clicking
select.
You see now it is selected in the root folder,
but I need to have another folder.
So I am going to type like a1111WebUI.
OK and then I am clicking I understand and
click install.
Now it will also download the necessary files
for me and we don't need to do anything manually.
During the download, it doesn't show you any
messages.
However, if you open your task manager with
right click and click task manager like here,
you can go to ethernet and you can see how
much download your computer is doing.
As you see, currently I am downloading like
100 megabits, which is my maximum bandwidth.
OK, after the file files has been downloaded,
it will quickly install them and it will open
the installed folder.
As you can see, the folder is like this.
Now we have launcher generated by our installer
and we have the GitHub folder of the official
Web UI.
It is this one and it has automatically downloaded
it for us and set it up.
And we have the launcher shortcut icon.
You can also pin this to taskbar, send it
to your desktop, whatever you do.
For example, I will send it to my desktop,
send to desktop.
And now in my desktop I have it and it has
been installed.
As you can see now, I am clicking finish and
now we can run it from directly from the launcher.
It is asking me asking me to do I want to
launch the from its shell command?
And I said yes.
And now the shell command has been run and
the automatic Web UI launcher has been started
so we can do automatic update.
As you can see, the arguments are getting
setted it in the left.
Automatic update extensions, clear generated
images.
You shouldn't pick this if you if you know
what you if you're not sure what is this doing.
Low VRAM.
If your graphic card is lower than 8GB, then
you should check this.
I have RTX 3060.
The RTX 3060 is a super card, super card for
machine learning tasks.
And I already have a video regarding that
on my channel.
If you wonder how powerful it is, you can
check that video, this one and read the comments
that people made.
You should also click enable xformers.
This enable xformers will improve your speed
if your graphic card is supporting that.
There are also optional checkpoint folders
and default vae files.
If you don't know this yet, you shouldn't
change them.
But if you want to learn more about them,
just go to our page, click videos.
And from here, find how to use stable diffusion
version 2.1 and different models in the web
UI video.
This video will help you tremendously to understand
them.
I will also put a link of this into the description
of the video.
There are also additional launch options,
and you can also type them.
Currently only this one is typed.
You should also type here.
--no-half.
This will make it work with stable diffusion
version 2.1.
And I am also explaining that in this video
as well, how to use stable diffusion 2.1.
And that's it.
That's all we need to start.
And then we click launch web UI.
It is generating a virtual environment for
Python.
This is only first time initialization and
you won't need it.
So you see it has installed Python 3.10 version.
This is one of the supported versions by the
web UI 3.10.8.
If you have different Python installations
in your computer, it is fine.
It will use the latest installed one because
I am assuming that the web this installer,
installer will set the default Python path
in the environment variables.
Now we are waiting it to install necessary
other files, for example, torch and torch
vision.
These are necessary to run the stable diffusion
model and generate images.
OK, so the installation has been completed.
You see, I don't have any error messages.
This is really important.
And then it will automatically start the web
interface that we can do image generation
and image manipulation with stable diffusion.
OK, by the way, you need a decent graphic
card to make it work with many of the features
of this AI model.
If you don't have such graphic card, then
on our channel, you can go to playlists.
And in here, click the stable diffusion and
watch these transform your selfie and how
to use SD 2.1 custom models on Google Colab.
Both of the videos explaining how to use stable
diffusion on a Google Colab notebook, which
uses the GPU provided by the Google.
So you don't need a strong GPU.
However, in this tutorial, we are going to
use our own computer's GPU.
As you can see, my GPU is already being used
a lot, but it is fine.
Now everything is ready.
First, we need to pick the model that we want
to use, which is this one automatically downloaded
and got ready for us.
Now we can enter prompts and generate images
and use all of all other features.
So in this video, I will just generate one
image.
Okay, I have entered my prompt as like this
and my negative prompt.
I have selected the sampling sampler as DPM++
SDE Karras and other options are like default.
If you want to learn more about this, please
watch the other videos in the channel because
these are all different things.
I will also show one another thing.
Just click this image and send to extras and
in here you can upscale it.
The one of the best upscaling algorithm I
have found is R-ESRGAN 4x+ and let's upscale
it to three times and just click generate.
This will also download another necessary
model file for R-ESRGAN 4x+.
It is not very big as you can see.
Then you will see it is generating the upscaled
image and it is ready.
When we click it now you see it is upscaled.
Okay, so this is all for automatic installation
with using the installer.
Now I will show how you can install and run
everything manually.
Okay.
The manual installation is tedious as you
can imagine.
First we are opening the GitHub repository
of the stable diffusion web UI.
I will put the link in the description.
Then click code and from here click local
and from here download as zip.
This will download the entire folder and it
is it has been downloaded pretty fast.
Cut it and then go to the folder that you
want to.
You want to install it.
So I will generate a new folder in C drive
and let's say webUI2 okay and paste it in
there.
And in here right click and extract here.
This is a zip file.
Okay I will cut and everything inside inside
here and I will paste them inside here.
Okay by the way, whenever the source code
gets updated in this repository, you have
to manually update it.
It won't be updated automatically.
Okay so to make this work, we need to have
installed python.
So how we are going to install python.
The suggested python version is python 3.10.6
and when you click it it will open all of
the python versions.
Do not download the latest python because
it won't work.
Some of the things are not compatible with
the latest version.
So from here we go to we are going to search
control-F 3.10.6 here and from here we go
to files and from here click windows installer
64 bit it will get installed.
Currently I have this installed but we can
reinstall it.
I am going to show in folder right.
Click and run as administrator.
Okay and in here you see there are install
now and customize installation and add python
to add python to path.
This is important.
If you don't make this, it won't work.
Okay I will click customization.
Everything is selected next.
Then you can pick the folder where you want
to install.
I want to install it in C drive with version
2 like this and you can also click precompile.
Okay this should be enough sufficient.
Click install.
Okay you see I have an error because another
version of this product is already installed.
Okay I am uninstalling the pythons version
3.11.0 and 3.10.8.
This is the one that has been installed by
the automatic installer and then we will manually
install this one to demonstrate.
Okay both python versions has been uninstalled,
so let's install 3.10.8 version.
Okay which is here I am clicking it I am clicking
the download.
I will also put a link of this into the description
show in folder right click run as administrator.
Okay you add python exe to path customize
installation.
Next, let's pick the folder to install.
Okay let's name it like this: precompile.
Okay install.
Okay now getting installed.
Hopefully it won't cause any errors.
Okay the python has been installed successfully.
Let's first verify it.
Open a command line window with typing cmd.
Like this command, prompt, enter and in here
just type python.
Okay you see my default python is 3.9.9 therefore,
it may not work and it will not work actually.
So I have to fix it from environment variables.
If you if you didn't have any installed python,
then it should automatically work for you.
So I am going to add I'm going to add it to
my edit path and in here I am going to move
I am going to add my new installation.
Actually it is on the top so probably I need
to change the path here.
Okay let's see the newest installation is
not here, so click new and from here.
Click browse in here.
Go to C drive where we installed it.
We installed it in let's see python.
Yeah, in here first selected.
Move it to the top.
Okay then I will just edit this actually the
bottom one.
Okay for editing, click edit and click browse
and go.
Okay in here python and in here I'm selecting
scripts okay, click okay, click okay and you
need to open another cmd command prompt window
type python.
Okay now you see my default python is 3.10.8.
Now we are ready to move to the next step.
So I am entering the folder where I have extracted
the GitHub files and in here first I need
to edit web user.bat file.
Right click it and click edit I need to add
2 command line arguments.
The arguments we need to add are --xformers
space character and --no-half and then click
save.
Okay now we are ready to launch the interface.
We are going to webui-user.bat and it will
generate first a virtual environment as same
as in the previous methodology.
Okay the installation has been completed,
but we have an error.
The error is that it says that we don't have
any model to run the stable diffusion.
So first we need to download and install our
model.
As I have already said multiple times, I am
fully explaining different models and how
to use them with the web ui in this tutorial
video.
So from here I am going to click official
repository actually not official repository.
So let's download not the official model,
but let's download anything v3 model: this
is a very famous model and from here I am
going to click anything v3.
I will use the pruned file.
Okay, just download it alternatively, you
can also download the official version just
click stable diffusion.
Actually, this could be hard.
So in google, just type stable diffusion version
1.5 if you type it to the google, it will
bring you the hugging face page.
From here and from here click files and versions
and from here click v1-5-pruned.ckpt and from
here click download it will get downloaded
like this as you can see.
Okay, once downloads has been completed, go
to your downloads folder, select the files,
click cut, and then go back to the installation
folder of the web ui and in here go to models
folder and in here go to stable diffusion
folder and this is the place where you are
going to paste, put your full models that
you have downloaded.
I am explaining everything in the other video
that I have mentioned and then go back to
web user dot file.
Okay, I'm closing the other command windows
and this time it will be much faster because
the initial step has been completed.
You see it is launching the web ui with the
arguments minus minus xformers and minus minus
no half.
Okay, okay so it is ready, but you see it
didn't open me any pages.
So you need to type this into your browser
or you can copy and paste it.
I am selecting it with my mouse right click
actually right click not working.
You need to select it with your mouse, then
control-c it will copy it and then you need
to paste it into your browser and it will
get opened.
Currently it is running.
Let's generate a new image with the same prompt.
I will post this prompt into the comments
section of the video.
I am selecting DPM++ SDE Karras this is the
sampling method and this is one of the good
ones that I have found.
Then click, generate and and you you are seeing
that it is generating each step.
You will see the progress here and also here.
Okay, the image has been generated, but you
see this is pretty different than the first
example.
Why?
Because currently it is using anything v3
model.
However, in the previous example, we were
using version 1.5 which was the official version.
If I change back model to that version and
generate another image, let's see what we
are going to get and this is what we get with
the official 1.5 version model.
Okay, this is all for today.
Please subscribe our channel and follow our
videos because I am planning to make a full
course regarding stable diffusion with explaining
pretty much everything about it.
You can see it in our playlist in the stable
diffusion.
I will put them with an order.
I am generating videos both for Google Colab
and that will run on your computer.
To make it run on your computer, you need
a decent graphic card.
You see, even my RTX 3060 is struggling a
little bit.
So therefore, if you don't have a strong GPU
you can use Google Colab or other services,
but they are a little bit harder to use than
installing on your computer.
Please also consider liking sharing this video,
subscribing, and also supporting us on patreon.
This will enable us to continue produce more
high quality videos in the future.
Currently, we still have zero patrons, but
I am hoping that you will be the first one.
Hopefully see you in another video.