Greetings everyone.
In this video, I will show you how you can use
Stable Diffusion 2.1 with Stable Diffusion
WebUI developed by Automatic1111.
I am working on a full course that will hopefully
explain every detail about how to use WebUI
to fully utilize Stable Diffusion.
So while I was trying to make version 2.1 work
with the WebUI, I had some difficulties.
So let me show you how you can make Stable
Diffusion 2.1 work with the WebUI.
This is the official page of the Stable Diffusion,
the Stability AI who releases the models.
And this is their Hugging Face page
where they release their models.
You see there are several models and Stable
Diffusion 2.1 and there is Stable Diffusion
2.1 base.
So you may ask what is the
difference of them.
The base version is 512 by 512 pixels and
the regular version is 768 and 768.
So this is the latest and
the better version.
I am going to use that on the WebUI.
So I am clicking Files and Versions and I am
going to download the file which is ema
pruned.
You see they are same file size.
So you may wonder what is the difference. Ema
is for further optimizing, further tuning
the model.
So usually it was larger size,
but now it is same size.
So it is better to use that.
You see now I am downloading the file.
Okay so the file has been downloaded.
Let's go to our Downloads folder quickly.
You see the file is here.
I am going to cut it.
And then where am I going to paste this is: I am
going to my installation of Stable Diffusion
WebUI and from there I am going to Models and from
there you see there is a Stable Diffusion
folder.
I am going to paste it there.
Are we done yet?
No, we are not done yet.
In the Stable Diffusion GitHub, there is a
file, it is inside the configs folder and
it is Stable Diffusion folder.
You see there are YAML files, this is for configuration
and for 768 pixels, we are going
to use the one ends with the V. Okay,
this is the file that we need.
We are going to click raw.
That's where I will put the links of these
files into the description of the video.
And in here we are going to click Save As.
We are going to save as this inside our installation,
we go to our Models folder and in there we
are going to Stable Diffusion folder
and we are going to save it in here.
Okay, are we done yet?
No.
This is saved as txt but its
extension has to be txt.
Its extension has to be YAML.
So if you are not able to see the extension
like this, you need to go to view and then
from here you see file name
and extension is checked.
If I uncheck it, it is displayed
like this and it won't work.
You need to check this from here and then you
need to right click, rename, delete the
dot txt, now click. Yes, it will become the correct
file extension, but we are still not
done yet.
We need to make these files same name. So I'm
going to right click and rename, I will copy
the name.
You can also use Ctrl C, Ctrl V or F2 to rename.
So when I click F2 it will automatically select
and I will do Ctrl V and it
will be pasted like this.
Okay, so now we are ready.
There is one final thing which is modifying the
command line of the BAT file that we are
running.
So I'm going to open it with right click and open
with, there is no open with, so I'm going
to open it with my text editor
which is notepad++.
You can also open it with notepad.
So to open it with notepad, I'm going to open
a notepad file like this and I'm going to
drag and drop it so it is opened
like this, you can see.
And from here we are going to set two command
line arguments which are like this: let me
zoom in, okay, --xformers
and --no-half.
xformers is for boosting performance, if your graphic
card is not supporting you don't need
to put this and this is necessary for the newest
version, it increases its precision.
So if you are wondering what are these command
line arguments, the command line arguments
of automatic1111 is released in its wiki.
Like this, I will also put this link into
the description and you see there are a lot
of command line arguments and you can see
what they are doing.
Okay so then we are saving it with file and
save and we are completely ready right now.
We are just clicking webui-user.bat and it will
start processing the necessary files.
Okay the messages displayed here is very important,
you see I have no error messages here, it
says that the config from this yaml is loaded and
the model file loaded from here, the weights
and xformers is applied and also it has loaded
the, let me see, hypernetwork that I have
developed and other things.
So I have no errors here, now we open the
webui like this, it shows the url in here
as you can see, you can
copy and paste that.
Okay from this left and top you can change the
models, so if I set the model like this,
let's see what happens.
Okay after I have restarted the application, I
am now able to change the model on runtime.
So you see now it is changing the
model, loaded model on runtime.
Okay currently the model is loaded and
our model is now 2.1 with 768 pixels.
Okay so I have made a test with version 1.5.
I have generated 9 images of futuristic tank
artwork with the other all generic keywords and
with generic keywords of negative prompt.
I will put all of these positive and negative
prompts into the description and the comment
section of the video, so don't worry.
I have used 20 sampling steps and DPM++ SDE Karras
as the sampling method. The native resolution
of 1.5 is 512 pixels by 512 pixels. So I didn't
change it. I made the batch count 9 and the
seed -1.
There is one another thing. Important thing that
I want to mention is that I have unloaded
all of the hypernetworks and embeddings. So this
is the raw test of the version 1.5, the
official version.
So each generation took about 15 seconds as you
can see on RTX 3060, okay and let's check
out the images right now.
So since they are native resolution 512 pixels,
their quality decreases when we display them
in a bigger screen like this.
The images like this.
I think they are pretty low quality. Since we
didn't use any artist style, we have only
used generic artworks, generic
keywords, okay.
Okay now we are seeing results of version 2.1
with the exactly same setup, exactly same
parameters, only I have changed it to native resolution
as can be seen here. 768 and I have
changed the model on the runtime as can be seen
here, you see it says that model loaded.
Let's check out the images
it has generated, okay.
So you see since the resolution is bigger, it
is looking better when we do increase in
size when displaying, okay.
Yeah definitely better than version 1.5 but this
is because in our prompts we didn't use
any of the style of the existing artists, okay.
We have only used the generic keywords.
That is why it is like this.
Also the inference time is more than two
times of the regular 1.5 version, okay.
So this time we are seeing analog diffusion results.
This is another model that is popular
so you see I have changed it on the runtime again
and it takes same about time. With the
original model 1.5. The results are like this
as you can see. I can say that it is not very
good by default for generating
this kind of images, okay.
To be able to use analog diffusion I have
downloaded the file from Hugging Face and
I have generated another YAML file as you can
see here, so where did I get this file?
This is the original 1.0 file which you can
find on this GitHub page. Let me show you,
it was, one second, here, yeah it is on this
page, it was also inside one of my folders.
So I have copied pasted there and it is the
same. I will also put link of this with the
same method as I have shown in the beginning,
you just save it and name it, okay.
Now this time we are seeing anything v3 model
results. I think it is pretty cool when we
consider it, it is older version 1.5 based
model, okay. Let's check it out, so I can
say that it is even better than version 2.1
as you can see, okay, I have used the same
setup and same settings, same prompt. So you
can try different models, it is always the
same principle. You download the model, you put
it inside the model folder and you generate
its YAML file, I don't know how this is pronounced,
so I am pronouncing it like that. You just
copy and paste this and rename it like this
one. So where you can get these models, you
can get those models on Hugging Face. So this
is the official repository. From here I am
clicking Stable Diffusion tag, so it is going
to search all models inside the Hugging Face
with Stable Diffusion tag and you see the Arcane
Diffusion or the anything v3, anything
v3 is in the top 4 actually as you can see here.
So you can also sort by recent updated
or you can sort by most likes, it is up to
you, you can try and test different models
from here, just download, copy, paste and change
the model from where, from here, click this
and it will refresh the models inside
your folder and you are ready to go.
I hope you have enjoyed our video, please consider
liking, sharing, commenting our video
to support us. And if you are generous, more
generous, you can also support us on Patreon
that would help us significantly to produce better
quality videos. So far we have 0 patrons,
but you may be the first one. Thank you very
much, hopefully see you in another video.